<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The praise of York-shire ale wherein is enumerated several sorts of drinks : with a description of the humors of most sorts of drunckards : to which is added, a York-shire dialogue, in its pure natural dialect, as</title>
            <author>Meriton, George, 1634-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50671</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16279</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12280248</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12280248</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58681</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50671)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58681)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 871:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The praise of York-shire ale wherein is enumerated several sorts of drinks : with a description of the humors of most sorts of drunckards : to which is added, a York-shire dialogue, in its pure natural dialect, as</title>
                  <author>Meriton, George, 1634-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Corrected and amended, with large additions im many places throughout the whole book /</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[6], 113 (i.e. 115), [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. White, for Francis Hildyard ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to George Meriton. cf. BM.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English language --  Dialects --  England --  Yorkshire.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58681:1"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58681:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The Praiſe of <hi>York-ſhire Ale</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherein is enumerated ſeveral Sorts of Drinks, with a Diſcription of the Humors of moſt ſorts of Drunckards.</p>
                  <p>To VVhich is added, a <hi>York-ſhire Dialogue,</hi> in its pure natural Dialect, as it is now commonly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenin the North parts of <hi>York-ſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BEING A Miſcellanious Diſcourſe or Hotch-potch of Several Country Affairs, begun by a <hi>Daughter</hi> and her <hi>Mother,</hi> and continued by the <hi>Father, Son, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle, Neece,</hi> and <hi>Land-Lord:</hi> after which follows a Scold between <hi>Nell</hi> and <hi>Beſs,</hi> two <hi>York-ſhire</hi> women.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Corrected and Amended, with large Additions in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places throughout the whole Book, by the</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>And after all, a</hi> Clavis <hi>explaining the meaning of all the</hi> York-ſhire <hi>words in the</hi> Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By</hi> G. M. <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ORK,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. White,</hi> for <hi>Francis Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ard,</hi> at the Signe of the Bible in Stonegate, 1685.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58681:2"/>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58681:2"/>
                  <head>To the READER.</head>
                  <l>Reader, heres ſportive mirth, and harmleſs Droll,</l>
                  <l>Come buy and read, &amp; laugh thy Belly full.</l>
                  <l>When thou haſt done, if thou condemn me for't,</l>
                  <l>Then I have made my ſelf, and not thee ſport;</l>
                  <l>That man is too moroſe, and much to blame,</l>
                  <l>That doth condemn all mirth to be profane:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58681:3"/>
All Ages have of lawful mirth allow'd.</l>
                  <l>If too much time in it were not beſtow'd;</l>
                  <l>Here thou haſt mirth, with ſmall expence of time,</l>
                  <l>I've taken pains, the pleaſure will be thine.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Vale,</salute>
                     <signed> G. M.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="epigraph">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58681:3"/>
                  <head>Ad Momum,</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Carpere vel noli, noſtra vel Ede tua.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Or Carpe not at theſe Lines of mine,</l>
                     <l>Or cauſe for to be publiſh'd thine.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58681:4"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58681:4"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The praiſe of</hi> Yorkſhire-Ale, <hi>wherein is Enumerated ſeveral Sorts of Drinks, with a Deſcription of the Humours of moſt Sorts of</hi> Drunkards.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>BAcchus</hi> having call'd a Parliament of late,</l>
                  <l>For to conſult about ſome Things of State,</l>
                  <l>Nearly concerning the honour of his Court,</l>
                  <l>To'th Sun, behind'th Exchange, they did reſort:</l>
                  <l>Where being met, and many things that time</l>
                  <l>Concerning the Adulterating Wine,</l>
                  <l>And other Liquors; Selling of Ale in Muggs,</l>
                  <l>Silver Tankerds, Black-Pots, and little Juggs:</l>
                  <l>Stronge Beer in Rabits, and cheating penny Cans,</l>
                  <l>Three Pipes for two pence; and ſuch like Trepans:</l>
                  <l>Vintners ſmall Bottles, Silver mouth'd black Jacks,</l>
                  <l>Papers of Sugar, with ſuch like cheating knacks:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:58681:5"/>
Biskets, <hi>Luke Olives, Anchoves, Caveare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neats Tongues, Weſt-Phalia-Hambs,</hi> &amp; ſuch like Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Crabs, Lobſters, Collar Beefe,</hi> Cold <hi>Pullets, Oyſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſuch like Stuffe, which make young men tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Royſte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>And many other things were then debated,</l>
                  <l>And Bills paſt, upon the Caſes ſtated;</l>
                  <l>And all things ready for Adjournment, then</l>
                  <l>Stood up one of the Northern Country men,</l>
                  <l>A Boon good fellow, and Lover of Strong Ale,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Tongue well ſteep'd in Sack begun this Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Bully Rocks, Ive been experienced long</l>
                  <l>In moſt of Liquors, which are counted Strong:</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Claret, White-wine</hi> and <hi>Canary Sack,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rheniſh</hi> and <hi>Malago,</hi> I've had no lack;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sider, perry, Metheglin,</hi> and <hi>Sherbet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Coffee</hi> and <hi>Mead,</hi> with <hi>Punch</hi> and <hi>Chocolet:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rum</hi> and <hi>Tea, Azora</hi> wine, <hi>Mederry,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vin-de-Paree, Brag,</hi> wine with <hi>Roſemdry:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58681:5"/>
                     <hi>Stepony, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquebath,</hi> beſides all theſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>qua Caeleſtis Cinnamon, Hearts-eaſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rave <hi>Roſa Solis,</hi> and other Liquors fine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>asberry Wine, Pur-royal,</hi> and <hi>Shampine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Malmſey,</hi> and <hi>Viper-wine,</hi> all theſe I paſs:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rontineack;</hi> with excellent <hi>Ipocras:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lac'd Coffee, Twiſt, Old Pharoh,</hi> and <hi>Old Hoc</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juniper, Brandy</hi> and <hi>Wine de Langue-Dock.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mum, Cherry-wine Langoon,</hi> and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>emonad,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sherry,</hi> and <hi>Port a Port,</hi> both white and red.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pomgranate, Mirtle,</hi> and <hi>Iſope-wine</hi> I know,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ipres</hi> and <hi>Orleance, Coos,</hi> and eke <hi>Anjow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Burgundian-wine, Coecubum, Sage</hi> and <hi>Muſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fennel</hi> and <hi>Wormwood-wine</hi> have paſt my Guſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hydromel, Mulſom,</hi> wine boil'd with <hi>Southernwood</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Opimium, Smirna,</hi> and <hi>Bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on</hi> good:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Temetum, Lora</hi> and brave <hi>Muskadel,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rumney</hi> and <hi>Nectar</hi> too that doth excell:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58681:6"/>
                     <hi>Sicilian, Naples</hi> and <hi>Lorain</hi> Wine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moravia, Malta</hi> and <hi>Corſica</hi> fine:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tent, Muskatine, Brandy,</hi> and <hi>Alicant,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of all theſe Liquors I've had no ſcant,</l>
                  <l>And ſeveral others; but none do I find,</l>
                  <l>Like Humming <hi>Northern ALE</hi> to pleaſe my mind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>It's pleaſant to the Taſte, ſtrong and mellow,</l>
                  <l>He that affects it not is no boon Fellow.</l>
                  <l>He that in this drink doth let his Senſes ſwim,</l>
                  <l>There's neither wind nor ſtorms will pierce on him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>It warms in Winter, in Summer opes the Pores,</l>
                  <l>'Twil make a Sovereign Salve 'gainſt cuts &amp; fores<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>It ripens Wit, exhillerates the Mind,</l>
                  <l>Makes friends of foes, &amp; foes of friends full kind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>It's Phyſical for old Men, warms their Blood,</l>
                  <l>Its Spirits makes the Coward's courage good:</l>
                  <l>The Tatter'd Beggar being warm'd with Ale,</l>
                  <l>Nor Rain, Hail, Froſt, nor Snow can him Aſſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58681:6"/>
He's a good man with him can then compare,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t makes a Prentiſe great as the Lord Mayor:</l>
                  <l>The Labouring Man, that toiles all day full ſore,</l>
                  <l>A pot of Ale at Night, doth him Reſtore,</l>
                  <l>And makes him all his Toil and paines forget,</l>
                  <l>And for another day-work, hee's then fit:</l>
                  <l>There's more in drinking Ale, ſure then we wot,</l>
                  <l>For moſt Ingenious Artiſts, love a Pot<hi>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nay amorous Ladyes it will pleaſure too,</l>
                  <l>Make frozen Maids, and Nuns, and Virgins do</l>
                  <l>The thing you know; Soldiers and Gown-men,</l>
                  <l>Rich and poor, old and young, lame &amp; ſound men</l>
                  <l>May ſuch advantage reap by drinking Ale,</l>
                  <l>As ſhould I tell, you'd think 'twere but a Tale;</l>
                  <l>Miſtake me not, Cuſtom, I mean not tho,</l>
                  <l>Of exceſſive Drinking, as great Ranters do,</l>
                  <l>For that would turn a great Wit to a Sot,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mean the merry Quibling o're a Pot,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58681:7"/>
Which makes dull Melancholy ſpirits be,</l>
                  <l>For Criticks and great Witts, good Company.</l>
                  <l>Oh the rare Virtues of this Barly Broth;</l>
                  <l>To rich and poor it's Meat and Drink and Clot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Court here ſtopt him, and the Prince did ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where may we find this Nectar, I thee pray,</l>
                  <l>The boon good Fellow anſwer'd, I can tell,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>North-Allerton,</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire</hi> doth excell</l>
                  <l>All <hi>England,</hi> nay all <hi>Europe</hi> for ſtrong Ale,</l>
                  <l>If thither we adjourn, we ſhall not fail</l>
                  <l>To taſte ſuch humming Stuff, as, I dare ſay,</l>
                  <l>Your Highneſs never taſted to this day.</l>
                  <l>They hearing this, the Houſe Agreed upon</l>
                  <l>All for Adjournmenr to <hi>North-Allerton:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Madam <hi>Bradley's,</hi> was the chief houſe then nam'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>There they muſt taſte this noble Ale ſo fam'd,</l>
                  <l>And nois'd abroad in each place far and near.</l>
                  <l>Nay, take it <hi>Bradley</hi> for ſtrong Ale and Beer,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58681:7"/>
Thou haſt it looſe, there's none can do ſo well</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> brewing Ale thou doſt all elſe excel.</l>
                  <l>Adjournment day being come there did appear</l>
                  <l>A brave fullhouſe, <hi>Bachus</hi> himſelfe was there.</l>
                  <l>This Nectar was brought in, each had his Cup,</l>
                  <l>But at the firſt they did but ſipple up</l>
                  <l>This rare <hi>Ambroſia,</hi> but finding that</l>
                  <l>'Twas grateful to the Taſte, and made them chat</l>
                  <l>And laugh and talk, O then when all was out,</l>
                  <l>They call'd for more, and drank full Cans about;</l>
                  <l>But in ſhort ſpace, ſuch ſtrange Effects it wrought</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the Courtiers, as <hi>Bachus</hi> never thought</l>
                  <l>Or dream'd upon: his wiſe men it made Fools,</l>
                  <l>And made his Councellors to look like Owls.</l>
                  <l>The ſimple ſort of Fellows it made prate,</l>
                  <l>And talk of Court Affairs, and things of State:</l>
                  <l>And thoſe that were dull Fellows when they came</l>
                  <l>Were now turn'd nimble Orators of Fame.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:58681:8"/>
And ſuch of them were thought to be no Wits,</l>
                  <l>Were Metamorphiſ'd into excellent Poets:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe that were lame, and came there with a ſtaff,</l>
                  <l>Threw't quite away, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> made the Prince to laugh,</l>
                  <l>The Cripples which did Crutches thither bring,</l>
                  <l>Without them now did hop about and ſing:</l>
                  <l>Some o're the Stools and Forms did skip and leap,</l>
                  <l>Som knac't their fingers, no plain word could ſpeak</l>
                  <l>Som ſhak'd their legs and arms with great delight,</l>
                  <l>Some curſt and ſwore, and others they did fight;</l>
                  <l>Some antick tricks did play like a Baboon,</l>
                  <l>Som knit their brows did ſhake their heads &amp; frown<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some <hi>Maudlin</hi> drunken were, and wept full ſore,</l>
                  <l>Others fell faſt aſleep, begun to ſnore:</l>
                  <l>Thouſands of Lies and Stories ſome did tell,</l>
                  <l>Their tongues went like the Clapper of a Bell,</l>
                  <l>Others were tongue-ti'd, could not ſpeak one word</l>
                  <l>And ſome did caſt their reckoning up at Board.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58681:8"/>
Some ſung aloud, and did deaf their fellowes</l>
                  <l>Making a Noiſe, worſe than <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulcan</hi>'s Bellows:</l>
                  <l>Some were for baudy Talk, and ſome did ſhout;</l>
                  <l>Some miſt the Cup, and pour'd the Liquor out?</l>
                  <l>At every word, ſome did their Neighbour jump,</l>
                  <l>And ſome did often give the Board a thump.</l>
                  <l>Some were all Kindneſs did their Fellows kiſs,</l>
                  <l>Som all bedaub'd their clothes, &amp; mouths did miſs:</l>
                  <l>For Arguments ſome were and learn'd diſcourſes,</l>
                  <l>Som talk'd of grey-hounds, ſom of running horſes,</l>
                  <l>Som talk'd of hounds, and ſome of Cocks o'th game</l>
                  <l>Som naught but hawks, and ſetting dogs did name:</l>
                  <l>Some talk'd of Battels, Sieges and great Warrs,</l>
                  <l>And what great Wounds &amp; Cutts they had, &amp; Scarrs</l>
                  <l>Some very Zealous were, full of Devotion,</l>
                  <l>But being Sober then had no ſuch Notion,</l>
                  <l>Some there Were all for drinking healths about</l>
                  <l>Others did rub the Table with their Snout:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58681:9"/>
Some piſs'd i'th fire, others threw out their ſnuffs,</l>
                  <l>And ſome were mad to be at handy Cuffs.</l>
                  <l>Some ſwore that they would have a <hi>Serenade,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Others did call their Hoſteſs Whore and Jade:</l>
                  <l>And round about did throw the Cups and glaſſes.</l>
                  <l>The drink did fly into their Neighbours Faces:</l>
                  <l>Some were for Bargains, ſome for Wagers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aying<hi>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Others for Cards and Tables cry'd for playing:</l>
                  <l>Some broke the Pipes, &amp; round about them threw,</l>
                  <l>Some ſmoak'd Tobacco till their noſe was blew.</l>
                  <l>Some in the fire fell and ſing'd their Cloaths,</l>
                  <l>And ſome fell from their Seat and broke their noſe</l>
                  <l>Some could not ſtir a Foot, did ſit and glore,</l>
                  <l>Some ſought the houſe all over for a whore,</l>
                  <l>Some call'd for Muſſck, others were for a dance,</l>
                  <l>And ſome lay ſtaring, as if in a Trance.</l>
                  <l>Some calld'd for Victuals others for a Cruſt,</l>
                  <l>Some op'd their Buttons and were like to Burſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58681:9"/>
Some challeng'd all the people that were there,</l>
                  <l>And ſome with ſtrange invented Oaths did Swear</l>
                  <l>Some told how many Women they had uſ'd,</l>
                  <l>Others at ſuch diſcourſe were ſore Amuſ'd:</l>
                  <l>Some ſhirk'd their drink, did put away the Cup,</l>
                  <l>And ſome took all that came left not one Sup:</l>
                  <l>Some whileſt they Sober were would nothing pay,</l>
                  <l>But being drunk, would all the Shot defray;</l>
                  <l>Others whileſt ſober, were as free as any,</l>
                  <l>But when once drunk, refuſe to pay one penny?</l>
                  <l>Some were for News, and how the State of things</l>
                  <l>Did ſtand amongſt great Potentates and Kings:</l>
                  <l>Some all their Friends &amp; Neighbours did backbite,</l>
                  <l>And ſome in Jearing others, took delight;</l>
                  <l>Some of their Birth and Riches made great boaſt.</l>
                  <l>And none but they were fit to Rule the Roaſt:</l>
                  <l>Some fill'd the Room with noiſe yet could not ſpeak</l>
                  <l>One word of <hi>Engliſh, Latine, French</hi> or <hi>Greek:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:58681:10"/>
Or any other Language which one might</l>
                  <l>Put into ſenſe, and underſtand aright:</l>
                  <l>Some Laught, until their Eyes did run on water,</l>
                  <l>And neither they, nor others knew the matter:</l>
                  <l>Some ſo miſchievous were they without Fear,</l>
                  <l>Would give their chiefeſt Friend a Box on'th Ear:</l>
                  <l>Some were ſo holy, that they would not hear,</l>
                  <l>Words either that Prophane or Smutty were:</l>
                  <l>Some in a Melancholly poſture laid,</l>
                  <l>Others did cry what is the Reckoning paid:</l>
                  <l>Some burnt their Hatts, others the Windowes broke</l>
                  <l>Some cry'd more Liquor we are like to Choake</l>
                  <l>Some piſs'd their Breetches, Sirreverence your Noſe,</l>
                  <l>Some not only piſs'd but all bee—their Hoſe:</l>
                  <l>Lame Gouty Men, did daunce about ſo ſprightly,</l>
                  <l>A Boy of fifteen ſcarce could skip ſo lightly:</l>
                  <l>Old crampy Capts that ſcarce a Sword could draw,</l>
                  <l>Swore now they'd keep the King of <hi>France</hi> in, Awe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58681:10"/>
And new Commiſſions get to Raiſe more Men,</l>
                  <l>For now they ſwore they were grown young again:</l>
                  <l>Off went their Perriwigs, Coats and Rapers,</l>
                  <l>Out went the Candles, Noſes for Tapers</l>
                  <l>Serv'd to give light, whilſt they did daunce around</l>
                  <l>Drinking full Healthes with Caps upon the ground:</l>
                  <l>And ſtill as they did daunce their round-delayes,</l>
                  <l>They all did cry this drink deſerves the Bayes,</l>
                  <l>Above all Liquors we have ever taſted:</l>
                  <l>It's pity that a drop of it were waſted:</l>
                  <l>A Stranger coming by, did hear the Noiſe,</l>
                  <l>He ſtep'd into the houſe to ſee the Boyes:</l>
                  <l>Such ſights he ſaw, as he nee'r ſee before,</l>
                  <l>Which made him Laugh untill his ſides were ſore,</l>
                  <l>His Horſe did follow, and ſaw their Quaffing,</l>
                  <l>He Neigh''d aloud, &amp; broke his Girts with laughing</l>
                  <l>Theſe Antick Sights made <hi>Bacchus</hi> to admire,</l>
                  <l>And then he did begin for to Enquire:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58681:11"/>
What Priviledges were beſtow'd upon</l>
                  <l>This famous Ale Town of <hi>North-Allerton,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Anſwer was, that it was only known,</l>
                  <l>To have four Fairs i'th year, a Bourrough-Town,</l>
                  <l>One Market every week and that was all,</l>
                  <l>This moved <hi>Bacchus</hi> preſently to call</l>
                  <l>For a great Jug which held about five Quartss</l>
                  <l>And filling't to the Brim; come here my Hearts</l>
                  <l>Said he, wee'l drink about this merry Health,</l>
                  <l>To the Honour of the Town, their State &amp; Wealth</l>
                  <l>For by the Eſſence of this Drink I ſwear,</l>
                  <l>This Town is Famous fot ſtrong Ale and Beer;</l>
                  <l>And for the ſake of this good Nappy Ale,</l>
                  <l>Of my great favour it ſhall never fail,</l>
                  <l>For to promote the quick Return and Trade,</l>
                  <l>For all ſtrong Ale and Beer, that here is made</l>
                  <l>So to't they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> went, and drunk full Healths about,</l>
                  <l>Till they drunk Money, Wit, and Senſes out:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:58681:11"/>
For whileſt one drop of Ale was to be had,</l>
                  <l>They Quaft, and drunk it round about like mad.</l>
                  <l>When all was off, then out they pull'd the Tapps,</l>
                  <l>And ſtuck the Spiddocks finely in their Hats,</l>
                  <l>And ſo Triumphantly away they went,</l>
                  <l>But they did all Agree with one Conſent</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Eaſingwold</hi> they then away would paſs,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Nanny Driffield</hi> there to drink a Glaſs:</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Bacchus</hi> having heard of her ſtrong Ale,</l>
                  <l>He ſwore by <hi>Jupiter,</hi> he would not fail</l>
                  <l>To have a merry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bout if he did find</l>
                  <l>Her Nappy Ale to pleaſe his Princely Mind:</l>
                  <l>When they came there a Flaggon was brought in,</l>
                  <l>Hold Gentlemen, before we do begin,</l>
                  <l>Cryes one Boon Blade, let me declare to you,</l>
                  <l>Some things which I of this ſame Ale doe know:</l>
                  <l>Soe bowing to the Prince, he thus began,</l>
                  <l>May't pleaſe your Highneſs, and you Gentlemen:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58681:12"/>
I've Travell'd thorow the moſt parts of <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As <hi>Picardy, Breſs, Bretaigne</hi> and <hi>Provence:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Normandy, Bevois<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Poictu</hi> and <hi>Champaigne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With <hi>Aquitain Bu gundy,</hi> and <hi>Lorrain:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Geneva, Savoy. Languedock;</hi> alſo</l>
                  <l>Within the Kingdome of <hi>Spain Oniedo:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lean, Navarr, Corduba,</hi> and ſoe on</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Biſcay, Toledo,</hi> and <hi>Catelone:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caſtile, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentia, Venice, Florence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mantua, Millain, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbin,</hi> St. <hi>Lawrence:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Portugall, Naples, Italy, Holland,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Germany, Denmarke, Sweedland, Poland.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hungary, Muſcovia, Cephalonia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turky, Tranſilvania,</hi> and <hi>Sclavonia:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Media, Perſia,</hi> and <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paleſtine, Armenia,</hi> and <hi>Arabia;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Parthia, Syria, Caldea,</hi> and <hi>Tartary,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt Indies, China,</hi> and <hi>Barbary:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:58681:12"/>
                     <hi>Numidia, Lybia,</hi> and <hi>Mexicana;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>thiopia, Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Meſſena;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eru,</hi> the <hi>Grecian Iſles, Sicillia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>anary Iſles, Corſica,</hi> and <hi>Sardinia.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heſe Country Wines, and other Liquors rare,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Englands</hi> humming Ale can not compare:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or in my thoughts it doth moſt drinks excell,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd this ſame Nappy Ale doth bear the Bell:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bove moſt Ale: for herein is ſuch Art,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome when you will it's neithe Sweet nor Tart,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Summer, Winter Weather, Raine, or Fair,</l>
                  <l>Thunder, Sunſhine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Miſty or ſerene Air:</l>
                  <l>Froſt or Snow, Morning, Noon, or Night,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> whem you pleaſe this Ale is alwayes Right<hi>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>either thicker, nor thinner, nor paler,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or higher Colour'd, Newer, nor ſtaler<hi>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onger, nor ſmaller, it hath no Fellow,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeter nor ſowrer, but alwayes Mellow:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:58681:13"/>
And fit to drink what time ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'er you come,</l>
                  <l>This is the pure ſtrong Brittiſh Iſlands Rum;</l>
                  <l>Hold, cry'd the Prince, for thou now more haſt ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Of this ſame Ale, then's Truth, I am affraid:</l>
                  <l>Yee Gods, the Prince then Cry'd, if this be true,</l>
                  <l>I'le leave my Government of Wine to you;</l>
                  <l>And liſt my ſelfe, mongſt Ale Boys that are famous,</l>
                  <l>For now, <hi>Paulo majora Canamus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So let us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> now fall on, fill up my Can,</l>
                  <l>Let each one take his Cup, obſerve his man,</l>
                  <l>And let us drink, until we all be Tipſie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ego tuquoque, ille &amp; ipſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vive Le Roy,</hi> great <hi>Bacchus</hi> then begins,</l>
                  <l>God bleſs him cry'd the Courtiers and his Friends;</l>
                  <l>This Health and ſeveral others went about,</l>
                  <l>Then growing warm, they all ſet up a ſhout;</l>
                  <l>Moſt famous Ale, if we thy worth had known,</l>
                  <l>Then we had haſted ſoone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to the Town,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:58681:13"/>
Oh Ladds ſaid <hi>Bachus</hi> I never thought t'have found</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch pleaſant Nectar, here on Engliſh ground</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wonder any will himſelfe Confine</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om bouſing Ale to ſwill himſelfe in Wine:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Juice of Grapes ſhall be no more o'th Quorum,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Nappy Ale, <hi>Hordia Far a Forum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wine's but an Aſs, when Ale doth come in play,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it be like the Ale we drink this day:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all in my Land-Lady let her Appear,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amous ſhe is for brewing Ale, I ſwear;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd I a badge of Honour will beſtow</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pon her without fail, before I go;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d ſo a Clerke was call'd to Exemplifie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Letters Pattents following, daintily:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>chus</hi> Prince of good Fellowes; To all to whom</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heſe our brave Letters Pattents ſhall now come,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hereas wee've bin Informed now of late,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et <hi>Nanny Driffield</hi> our great Court and State,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58681:14"/>
For many years laſt paſt hath much advanc'd,</l>
                  <l>By her ſtrong humming Ale and as it chan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>We having ample Proofe thereof, ſo now</l>
                  <l>We of our Princely grace, would have you kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>This Land-Lady unto the Noble State</l>
                  <l>And Honour of a Counteſs, we Create:</l>
                  <l>And by our merry Fudling Subjects, She</l>
                  <l>Counteſs of <hi>Stingo</hi> henceforth call'd ſhall be.</l>
                  <l>To'th Pattent then was fixed a Black Pot,</l>
                  <l>In a fine Silk Lace, twiſted on a knot:</l>
                  <l>Upon the Counteſs it was then beſtow'd,</l>
                  <l>The Noble Courtiers all ſtood up and Bow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Long may your Honour Live to Brew ſuch A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>And of your Art we wiſh you never fail;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bachus</hi> then took a great full Flagon up,</l>
                  <l>And drunk the Counteſs health left not one S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>To an old Blade, the Prince ſaid, thou ſhalt follo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then, <hi>Tu-eris mihi magnus Apollo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58681:14"/>
Each of the Courtiers did then pledge the ſame,</l>
                  <l>And now in earneſt did begin the game:</l>
                  <l>The new made Counteſs to gratifie them all,</l>
                  <l>For an Hogshead of her choiſeſt Ale, did call:</l>
                  <l>Upon the Hogshead <hi>Bachus</hi> got aſtride,</l>
                  <l>Now Ladds ſaid he, this Ale is Deified.</l>
                  <l>A Counteſs, a Counteſs, they then proclaim'd,</l>
                  <l>You all the Country o're, will now be Fam'd:</l>
                  <l>Drink Prince ſhe ſaid, and all ye Noble Crew;</l>
                  <l>Drink till ſuch time, ye wade your Noſes blue:</l>
                  <l>Here's Ale ſaid they, ſo pure, ſo clear, ſo fine,</l>
                  <l>It is more grateful to the taſte then Wine:</l>
                  <l>Nay this ſame Ale will make the World admire us</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Efficit Ingenios nobilis Ala <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iros:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This famous Liquor, we know doth far outgoe</l>
                  <l>The Poets Nectar and <hi>Ambroſia</hi> too:</l>
                  <l>The Gods <hi>Nepenthe</hi> with it cannot compare,</l>
                  <l>This is the Soveraign Antidote 'gainſt Care.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58681:15"/>
Some Townſmen hearing this, Liſtened a while,</l>
                  <l>Then into'th Houſe they went, begun to ſmile;</l>
                  <l>You'r welcome Gentlemen, ſit down ſaid the Prince</l>
                  <l>And do as we do: if it be no Offence</l>
                  <l>The townſmen ſaid, wee'l joyn our ſelves with you,</l>
                  <l>And try this day, to whom Honour is due</l>
                  <l>Whether to Wine or Ale; it ſhall be Try'd,</l>
                  <l>Agreed Agreed, they with one voice all Cry'd</l>
                  <l>The Townſmen did perceive the Courtiers warm,</l>
                  <l>Six in a hand ſayes one will do no harm:</l>
                  <l>You Grape Boyes now ſhall know before we part,</l>
                  <l>Wines not the only Nouriſher of Art:</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Recubans ſub Teguine Fagi</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We drink ſtrong Ale: it makes us of the <hi>Magi.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Well ſaid, cry'd <hi>Bacchus,</hi> about then let it goe,</l>
                  <l>As long as any here can ſhake a Toe:</l>
                  <l>For as <hi>Scribendo diſces Scribere,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Juſt ſo <hi>Bibendo diſces Bibere<hi>:</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:58681:15"/>
O brave <hi>Colonus</hi> ſee it go about,</l>
                  <l>And let us now all Joyne ſet foot to foot,</l>
                  <l>And drink all off, I'le not contend for praiſe,</l>
                  <l>From henceforth this ſame Ale ſhall have the Bayes</l>
                  <l>Wine ſhall not once be nam'd, where this comes in,</l>
                  <l>He that names Wine that day commits a Sin,</l>
                  <l>Wee'l all be merry, I'le hear no Clamour,</l>
                  <l>Let's drink and ſing, <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inia vincit Amor.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Health upon Health did poſt about with ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>Till all the Courtiers were ſore fluſht indeed:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui Color albus erat,</hi> with a <hi>Faldo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I plainly ſee <hi>Nunc eſt contrarius Albo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>One Townſman ſaid: let us our hold now keep:</l>
                  <l>And we ſhall quickly lay them all to ſleep,</l>
                  <l>Bumpers and double Tankerds did go round,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bachus</hi> from's hogſhead Throne, fell to the ground,</l>
                  <l>Some forwards fell, backwards, and ſidewayes ſome,</l>
                  <l>Till on to'th Floor, they all did tumble down:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:58681:16"/>
Let's throw them on an heap, a Townſman ſaid,</l>
                  <l>And Sing a Catch about them; I have made,</l>
                  <l>Agreed they cry'd the Wine Boyes this ſhall know,</l>
                  <l>That they to good Ale Topers, now muſt bow:</l>
                  <l>Lett's throw the God above, Hee'l ſpoil his Cloath;</l>
                  <l>Marry ſayes one, I think hee's broke his Noſe,</l>
                  <l>He hath all bedaub'd his Suit of Tabby,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Sorte tua contentus Abi,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Said they; The Catch begun then by the Blades,</l>
                  <l>The Tune is, Hail unto the Myrtle Shades.</l>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="song">
                              <pb n="25" facs="tcp:58681:16"/>
                              <head>The Song.</head>
                              <lg n="1">
                                 <head>1.</head>
                                 <l>COlonus <hi>and</hi> Bacchus <hi>did meet,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Each one to commend his own Liquor;</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>The Juice of the Grape was ſweet,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>But Barley Oyle ran down the quicker:</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Colonus <hi>did challenge the Gods,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>To ſight in defence of his Barley,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>But</hi> Bacchus <hi>perceiving the odds,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Deſir'd a Friendly Parly.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg n="2">
                                 <head>2.</head>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>They drunk full Bumpers about,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>And</hi> Bacchus <hi>an health did begin,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>The</hi> Bacchanalians <hi>gave a great ſhout,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>The</hi> Colonians <hi>then thronged faſt in:</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <pb n="26" facs="tcp:58681:17"/>
                                    <hi>They drunk double Tankards around,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Till the Grape Boyes begun for to Glore</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>The Ruſticks neer flinched their ground,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Till</hi> Bacchus <hi>fell down on the Floor:</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg n="3">
                                 <head>3.</head>
                                 <l>Colonus <hi>did heartily Laugh,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>And about the God they did daunce,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Full Pots about they did quaff:</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Whileſt</hi> Bacchus <hi>lay ſtill in a Trance.</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>The Grape Boyes were beat out of play,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>And at length poor</hi> Bacchus <hi>did Riſe:</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>To</hi> Colonus <hi>he yeilded the day,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>So the Ruſticks obtained the Prize.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </lg>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58681:17"/>
Juſt as the Catch did end, they rubb'd their Eyes,</l>
                  <l>They Yawn'd and gap'd, and did begin to riſe:</l>
                  <l>Oh Gentlemen, the Townſmen ſaid you now,</l>
                  <l>We hope the force and power of Ale doe know:</l>
                  <l>Faith <hi>Bacchus</hi> ſaid wee'r forc'd to yeild the day,</l>
                  <l>For you have beat us quite, Pinch out of Play:</l>
                  <l>O Wine I formerly did thee adore,</l>
                  <l>But thou ſaid he ſhall have my heart no more:</l>
                  <l>Boy lead our Horſes out when we get up,</l>
                  <l>Wee'l have with you, a merry Stirrup Cupp:</l>
                  <l>Then we to Famous <hi>Yorke</hi> will haſt away,</l>
                  <l>For thither wee'l adjourn the Court this day:</l>
                  <l>The Horſes were lead out, they mounted all,</l>
                  <l>And each of them did for a Flagon call:</l>
                  <l>Well Sirs ſaid they, we yeild the day's your own,</l>
                  <l>Wee'l try again next time we come to Town,</l>
                  <l>Agreed the Townſmen ſaid, come when you will,</l>
                  <l>You'l find us true blue Fudling Bulies ſtill:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58681:18"/>
They drunk about, the Townſmen pledg'd the ſame</l>
                  <l>So took their leaves till they ſhould meet again</l>
                  <l>At parting they did kiſs, and <hi>Bachus</hi> ſwore,</l>
                  <l>He never met with ſuch boon Blades before:</l>
                  <l>Well noble Boyes ſaid He, before't be long</l>
                  <l>I hope our Lot will be to ſing a Song;</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Bacchus</hi> when you come the Townſmen ſaid</l>
                  <l>Come well prepar'd, for we are not afraid:</l>
                  <l>Farewell good Lads ſaid he, and ſo away,</l>
                  <l>They took their journey unto <hi>Yorke</hi> that day:</l>
                  <l>When they to <hi>Yorke</hi> were come, they rov'd about</l>
                  <l>From Houſe to Houſe to find ſuch Nectar out</l>
                  <l>As they had taſted laſt at length they heard</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Parkers</hi> Coffee-houſe i'th Minſter Yard:</l>
                  <l>They ſeveral ſorts of ſtrong Ale there would find</l>
                  <l>Some of which Ale would ſurely pleaſe their mind</l>
                  <l>Unto this place they went, and Crowded in,</l>
                  <l>Come Wench ſaid they, with ſtrong Ale wee'l begin</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58681:18"/>
Sirs ſaid the Girle, wee've Ale that's ſtrong &amp; old,</l>
                  <l>Both from <hi>North-Allerton,</hi> and <hi>Eaſingwold.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>Sutton, Thirke,</hi> likewiſe from <hi>Raſcal</hi> Town,</l>
                  <l>Wee've Ale alſo thats call'd <hi>Knocker-down:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Well bring a Tankerd of each in, you Maid,</l>
                  <l>Wee'l taſte them every one the Courtiers ſaid;</l>
                  <l>The Ale came in each man a Tankard had,</l>
                  <l>They taſted all; And ſwore they were full glad</l>
                  <l>Such Stingoe, Nappy, pure Ale they had found:</l>
                  <l>Lett's looſe no time ſaid they but drink a round:</l>
                  <l>And chear our Spirits up with this good Creature,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Miſer eſt, qui Nummos Admiratur.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>About and about it went full merrily,</l>
                  <l>Till ſome could neither go, ſtand, ſit, nor ſee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vir ſapit qui pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ca loquitur;</hi> if true</l>
                  <l>The wiſeſt in the Company is you,</l>
                  <l>Said one, to's Oppoſite beyond the Table,</l>
                  <l>Who was ſo drunk, to ſpeake he was not able:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:58681:19"/>
They call'd &amp; drank till they were all high-flown,</l>
                  <l>And could not find their way into the Town,</l>
                  <l>They ſtaggar'd too and fro, had ſuch lite heads,</l>
                  <l>That they were guided all unto their Beds:</l>
                  <l>And in the Morning when they did awake,</l>
                  <l>They curſt and ſwore that all their heads did ake;</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Yorke-ſhire Yorke-ſhire:</hi> thy Ale it is ſo ſtrong;</l>
                  <l>That it will kill us all, if we ſtay long:</l>
                  <l>Soe they agreed a Journey for to make</l>
                  <l>Into the South, ſome Reſpite there to take,</l>
                  <l>But in ſhort ſpace again they ſaid they'd come,</l>
                  <l>And Taſt ſome more of this ſame <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi> Hum:</l>
                  <l>Nay <hi>Bacchus</hi> ſwore to come he would not fail,</l>
                  <l>And glut himſelfe with <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi> Nappy Ale:</l>
                  <l>It is ſo pleaſant, mellow too, and fine,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Bachus</hi> ſwore hee'd never more drink Wine.</l>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:58681:19"/>
                     <head>The Concluſion.</head>
                     <l>Now I have done, and will hold a piece on't:</l>
                     <l>That, <hi>Nil hic Niſi Carmina deſunt.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Some men will ſay perhaps, here is no wit,</l>
                     <l>Let ſuch then know, <hi>Ex Nihilo Nihil fit.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58681:20"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58681:20"/>
A York-ſhire DIALOGUE In its pure Natural DIALECT As it is now commonly ſpoken in the North parts of <hi>Yorkeſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Being a Miſcellaneous Diſcourſe or Hotch-Potch of ſeveral Country Affairs, begun by a Daughter, and her Mother, and continued by the Father, Son, Uncle, Neeſe, and Land-Lord, after which followes a Scould between <hi>Beſs</hi> and <hi>Nell</hi> two <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi> Women.</p>
                  <p>Note that <hi>D.</hi> ſtands for Daughter, <hi>M.</hi> for Mother, <hi>F.</hi> for Father, <hi>S.</hi> for Son, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi> for Uncle, <hi>N.</hi> for Neeſe, and <hi>L.</hi> for Land-Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reader here's Folly come and Laugh thy fill, He neer did good, that never did no ill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YORK</hi> Printed by <hi>J. White,</hi> for <hi>Francis Hildyard</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Stonegate.</hi> 1684.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58681:21"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="dialogue">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58681:21"/>
                  <head>A Yorkeſhire Dialogue in its pure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Dialect, &amp;c.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <l>MOther our Crockey's Cawven ſine't grew dark,</l>
                     <l>And Iſe flaid to come nar, ſhe macks ſike warke,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Seaun, ſeaun, Barne, bring my Skeel and late my Tee:</l>
                     <l>Mack haſt and hye thee ore to'th Laer to me:</l>
                     <l>Weeſe git a Battin and a Burden Rape,</l>
                     <l>Though it be mirke, weeſe late it out by grape:</l>
                     <l>Then wee'l to'th Field &amp; give the Cow ſome Hay</l>
                     <l>And ſee her Cleen before ſhe come away:</l>
                     <l>For flaid ſhe git ſome watter before ſhe Cleen.</l>
                     <l>And mar her Milk, Iſe greet out bath my Neen:</l>
                     <l>D. Whaugh Mother how ſhe rowts, Iſe varra Arfe,</l>
                     <l>Shee'l put and rive my good Prunella Scarfe:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:58681:22"/>
Iſe ding thy Harnes out, thou baſe mucky Sew,</l>
                     <l>Thou macks ſike Anters, thou'l miſtetch my Cow:</l>
                     <l>What need thou be ſeay flaid, ſhe will nut mell,</l>
                     <l>Nor hipe, if there war nean here but thy ſell:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <l>Wally, wally, heres a deft Tinye, Cawfe,</l>
                     <l>It's better than a Keauſteril behawfe,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>But pratty macks nea Porridge <hi>Tibb,</hi> ift wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>A Keauſteril, it wad yeild mare money far:</l>
                     <l>It's newly gitten Feaut, tack haud on't <hi>Tibb,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wee'l Suck'lt weel, and put it into'th Cribb,</l>
                     <l>And Bed it ſtrangly with good clean Streay,</l>
                     <l>And ſee it lye'th ſell down, before we geay;</l>
                     <l>It liggs bravely, for't hardly can be ſeen,</l>
                     <l>It'l git neay Cawd, it's bedded up to'th Een:</l>
                     <l>Good Beddin <hi>Tibb,</hi> will mack if Battin wee'l,</l>
                     <l>Now I will milk ſome Beeſtlings into'th Skeel;</l>
                     <l>Our Why is better Tidded than this Cow,</l>
                     <l>Her Ewr's but ſwampe, Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e's nut for Milk I trow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:58681:22"/>
You wait nut yet of Croky what to ſay,</l>
                     <l>Preaufe of a Puddin's it'h eating alway:</l>
                     <l>Shee's daft yet on her Cawf, in a day or tweay</l>
                     <l>You'l ſee, wheather ſhe be for Milk or neay;</l>
                     <l>Now let us hame and late for Bowls and Sile,</l>
                     <l>Thy Fatther'l meauſe whore weare all this while.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Iſe nut farr, iſt Cow Cawv'd that's a Goodin,</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>Tibb</hi> weeſe git ſome Beeſtling Pudding:</l>
                     <l>Letts ſpang our geates for it is varra Snithe,</l>
                     <l>And Iſe flaid Wife it will be Froſt Belive;</l>
                     <l>Leauk yonder iſt Lad coming to late for you,</l>
                     <l>Hee'd be in Bed to Morn we gang to Plewe:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Wya, wya, did'th Pot play when you com,</l>
                     <l>wheay keauks the Supper now when Iſe fra Hame</l>
                     <l>What <hi>Hobb</hi> iſt Beefe aneugh, iſt Groats put in,</l>
                     <l>Till all war deaun, I knaw thou wad nut lin:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S.</speaker>
                     <l>Ey Mother, Groats are in Iv'e tane of'th Pot,</l>
                     <l>And 'th Cael I ſeaure are caud anough to ſup:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:58681:23"/>
                        <hi>M.</hi> Come tack up'th Beefe <hi>Tibb,</hi> iſt Dubler ready,</l>
                     <l>Thy Father and <hi>Hobb,</hi> mun gang to'th Smiddy,</l>
                     <l>And fetch the Specks, Sock and Cowlter hither</l>
                     <l>Seed time's now come they mun ſaw Haver<hi>:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Come <hi>Tibb</hi> for ſham bring out the bread &amp; ſawt</l>
                     <l>Thou's lang a coming, thou braids of Haver Maut</l>
                     <l>Thur Cael taſt ſtrang of Reeke, they're nut for me,</l>
                     <l>God ſends meat and'th Deevil ſends Ceauks I ſee:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Marry geaupe ſtink, you're varra dench'd I trow</l>
                     <l>Your Belly ſarraes an ill Maſter now:</l>
                     <l>They'ro're good for them that finnds faut I ſeaure,</l>
                     <l>But as the Sew doth fill the Draffe doth ſoure:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou wad faine perſwade us they are gooddins,</l>
                     <l>Hungry Doggs are fain of durty Puddins:</l>
                     <l>Come thou and taſte them, and ſit down i'th chair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Meay the merryer, but fewer better Fair.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>But you will nut let me be merry lang</l>
                     <l>I ſeaur, for there is allwayes ſomething wrang</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58681:23"/>
They that have ſike as you, can have neay will</l>
                     <l>To deau ought, A good Jack macks a good Gill,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>I pray thee <hi>Pegg</hi> let us be Friends again,</l>
                     <l>Thou knaws fair words duz mack Feauls fain,</l>
                     <l>It is weel ſpoken, that's weel tane I've heard,</l>
                     <l>Thou is ſeay Crabb'd, to ſpeak Iſe alwayes feard:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſet yan on unſcape, and than you rewe,</l>
                     <l>Great matters of an angry word I trowe;</l>
                     <l>Stride <hi>Tibb,</hi> &amp; clawt ſome Caſſons out o'th Hurne,</l>
                     <l>Than geay thy wayes and fetch a Skeel of Burn,</l>
                     <l>And hing the Pan ore'th fire ith Rekin-Creauk,</l>
                     <l>And Iſe weſh Sile, and Diſhes up 'ith Neauke:</l>
                     <l>And then wee'l all to Bed; here's a cawd Neet:</l>
                     <l>But Husband Iſe cling cloſe, and weeſe blend feet</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray thee deau <hi>Pegg,</hi> than Iſe git up 'ith Morne</l>
                     <l>And Late ſome Pokes, and put up our ſeed Corn:</l>
                     <l>Than thou may ſarra Gawts and Gilts with Draffe,</l>
                     <l>And Iſe give'th Yawds ſome Hinderends and Caffe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:58681:24"/>
Than for our Breakfaſts thou may haet ſome Cael<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Till I lie by my Shackfork, and my Flail;</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Hobbs</hi> mack ready my Harrows, &amp; my Plewgh</l>
                     <l>And he and I <hi>Pegg</hi> fall deau weel aneugh;</l>
                     <l>I've heard it tawk'd and now the Trueth I've fund</l>
                     <l>A mell tweay Steauls, the Tail may fall to'th grund</l>
                     <l>I lited on <hi>Hobb,</hi> and he lited on me,</l>
                     <l>And the Dee'l a thing is ready that I ſee;</l>
                     <l>Neither Traces, Hames, nor Baurghwans to finnd,</l>
                     <l>Swingle-Trees nor Helters, all's made an ill end:</l>
                     <l>But tweay dayes ſine, Iſe ſeaure they war all here</l>
                     <l>Flung on an heap ith midſt of our Laer Fleaure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S.</speaker>
                     <l>Fatther they're liggin all on our Faugh Lands.</l>
                     <l>I trail'd them there my ſell with my awn hands,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Thous a good Lad my <hi>Hobb</hi> that teauk ſike care</l>
                     <l>Iſt Yoakes and Bowes and Gad &amp; Yoakſticks there:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S.</speaker>
                     <l>Ey, ey, &amp; 'th Pleugh Staffe teau, Hopper &amp; Teems</l>
                     <l>We lack nought but a Bay Stagg of my Neems,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58681:24"/>
That wee're to Yoak 'ith Plewgh before our Yawds</l>
                     <l>And than Iſe ſeaur weeſe rive up all Adawds,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Near rack, near rack, weeſe tack neay thought for that</l>
                     <l>Iſe ſeaur that it will bide us billing at.</l>
                     <l>Our Land is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wgh, and full of ſtrang whickens.</l>
                     <l>Cat whins, and Seavy Furs, and monny Breckins:</l>
                     <l>It's nought but Gorr, it ploſhes under Feaut,</l>
                     <l>Weeſe find Trouble aneugh when we come teaut:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S.</speaker>
                     <l>Lythe ye, lythe ye, how fondly you tawke,</l>
                     <l>You think weeſe mack monny ilfavart Bawke;</l>
                     <l>When we do Plew, we mun tack teaume I Reed.</l>
                     <l>I've heard Fowks often ſay mare heaſt warſe ſpeed:</l>
                     <l>The Feck on'ts Gripp'd, and 'th watter runs away,</l>
                     <l>I was at field my ſell, and ſaw't to day:</l>
                     <l>It will bring as good Blendings I dare ſay,</l>
                     <l>As ever grew a Reaut in onny Clay;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Our Eard is nut for blending <hi>Hobb</hi> I dout,</l>
                     <l>We mun ſaw it with Bigg I trow, or nought:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58681:25"/>
Gray Geauſe hes laid, geay carry in her Egg,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tibb</hi> dar nut come to fetcht, for flaid o'th Stegg,</l>
                     <l>Than goame ſteek'th Hemble deaur, &amp; bar up Griſe</l>
                     <l>For they've byn in a miſchief twice or thrice;</l>
                     <l>Let's nut loaſe an Hogg for a hawpworth of Tarr,</l>
                     <l>But mind to Noint'h Gawt Ear it will all marr,</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Perry</hi> garr'd him run, and lugg'd him ſayer,</l>
                     <l>I thowght that he had riven off his Ear:</l>
                     <l>The Libber coms to Moarn, weeſe libb'th awd Piggs</l>
                     <l>For they've made filthy warke ot'h Corn Land Rigs</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S.</speaker>
                     <l>Fatther our Bull Segg's puſlom'd, hee's deg bownd</l>
                     <l>And our awd Meer is ſlidden into'th Pownd,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Wellaneerin, wellaneerin, run faſt run,</l>
                     <l>Run faſt <hi>Hobb,</hi> and bid my <hi>Maugh Herry</hi> come:</l>
                     <l>And bring his Horne, and give our Segg a drink,</l>
                     <l>Mack haſt or elſe Iſe whang thee till thou ſtink:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</speaker>
                     <l>How now <hi>Hob</hi> thou reeks fair, what macks ta run</l>
                     <l>What uncuths hes ta brought come tell me ſeaun,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:58681:25"/>
Our Yawd's layd backwards, Bull Seg is like to dee</l>
                     <l>And ſeay Iſe come for you to gang with me:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi> Marry Iſe vara weay, for that's ill warke,</l>
                     <l>Iſe flaid weeſe nut git there, before't be darke,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>That's weel your come, the Segg is at Stand Heck</l>
                     <l>What ails this deaur, I cannut finnd out'th Sneck:</l>
                     <l>That comes in an hour, ſometimes they ſay,</l>
                     <l>That comes nut in Twenty, He was weel to day,</l>
                     <l>And preaz'd to git ore'th Hedge into our Fogg,</l>
                     <l>And I did Slate him back than with our Dog;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</speaker>
                     <l>Is this him that liggs here, Hee's Teng'd hee'l dee</l>
                     <l>Lets ſtick him, ther's neay whopes of him I ſee</l>
                     <l>Hee's pratty meeterly Fleſh, here's a good Skin,</l>
                     <l>Hee'l mack good Cael, and put fat Backon in,</l>
                     <l>Lets gang and ſee your Sheep, what ails yon Teaup,</l>
                     <l>I think ſomething hes ſtampt upon his Feaut:</l>
                     <l>Thur Yowes are Clowelagg'd, they skitter ſaire,</l>
                     <l>They'l be full of Mawks if you tack nut Care;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:58681:26"/>
I think they've gitten ſome freſh whewts of Girſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>That macks them ſeay beclarted about'th Arſe</l>
                     <l>Iſe like to clem let's Hame <hi>Maugh</hi> to our <hi>Pegg,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sheel kedge our kites with good Kirne-milk, &amp; whig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</speaker>
                     <l>Siſter heve you ought that will ſlocken weel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>You've Whigg 'ith Stand, &amp; good Kirn-milk 'ith Skee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fill me 'th bend Kit Iſe ſet it to my pact,</l>
                     <l>Ile venture a ſtrang pull though I be haet,</l>
                     <l>Here's fine Backon Siſter its glore Fat,</l>
                     <l>But it's a little knarl'd with your Carl Cat,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>It's ſmall warſe <hi>Pegg</hi> whores our Haver Riddle,</l>
                     <l>Laſt time I ſaw't it was laid ive our Stable:</l>
                     <l>Iſe like to tawme this day's ſeay varry warme</l>
                     <l>Your Bees macks a great noiſe, you'l have a Swarm</l>
                     <l>Wheay has remmond 'th ſide Lanyels ſome ill Foal</l>
                     <l>I laid um here, under the Awmry ſoal,</l>
                     <l>Can neathing ligg that's leeter than a Stane</l>
                     <l>We ſall heve nought left ſeaun, all will be gane</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58681:26"/>
All things run wrang Wife, neathing Cottens weel</l>
                     <l>The Spindle is a Ravel'd, neay Garn o'th Reel,</l>
                     <l>Thy Rock is burnt, thy Sneauſkin is quite gean,</l>
                     <l>I've lated ſayer, and can nut finnd it Dame;</l>
                     <l>Our great whean Cat hes eaten'th Pudding poke,</l>
                     <l>You goam neathing, I never ſaw ſike Fowke:</l>
                     <l>Our Kitling meyw'd, I meauſ'd what ſhe did aile,</l>
                     <l>I trail'd her out 'oth Ream Kit, by the Taile;</l>
                     <l>Our Sew hes been 'ith Spence, thrawn down Whigg Stand</l>
                     <l>I ſet it up again, with my awn hand:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Perry</hi> hes been ith Beef Tubb teau juſt now,</l>
                     <l>And maed as bad, or warſe warke, than our Sew<hi>:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Ewn for lack of Dittin, hes ſlake'd all'th heet.</l>
                     <l>Puddings and Pyes are daugh nut fit to Eat,</l>
                     <l>Thy Sammaron web thou ſent to'th Bleacher well,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s ſtown, gray Geauſe Geſlings all daz'd 'ith ſhell:</l>
                     <l>Our Bakin I put up 'ith Harden Seek,</l>
                     <l>The Milners let it fall into the Beck.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58681:27"/>
Waies is me Husband, our awd Bread's all gane</l>
                     <l>We mun mack bannocks till'th Bakin come hame</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>It comes ith Earnder Wife or elſe by Neaun,</l>
                     <l>Come bring my Slippers <hi>Tibb,</hi> and deet my Sheaun</l>
                     <l>To Morn 'ith Ownder we mun dod our Sheep<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Weathers haet and Mawkes begin to Creepe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Some's feal'd our Backſton <hi>Tibb,</hi> or elſe it's gan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Iſe varra flaid ſome's gitten't for'th lang lane:</l>
                     <l>If I cud tell wheay's cutt our Band fra'th Sneck,</l>
                     <l>Next time they come, Iſe mack them Jet the Heck,</l>
                     <l>Thou geayes <hi>Tibb</hi> like a Feaul, come leauke about,</l>
                     <l>And ſee if thou can late our Backſtane out<hi>:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <l>There is ſeay monny Holes and Hurles to ſeek</l>
                     <l>That Iſe neer finnd it, if I late this Week:</l>
                     <l>Some Tantril hes byn here and Stown't away,</l>
                     <l>For it was liggin here, but tother day:</l>
                     <l>Whilk wayes our <hi>Hobb</hi> gane Mother, heres baſe wark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yonders Gawt ith Garth, hes riven all his Sarke</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:58681:27"/>
What's warſe than ill Luck, late me our Fruggin</l>
                     <l>Iſe ſtopp'th Yat, till thou mack <hi>Perry</hi> lugg him:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Here'ſt Dubler broken, &amp; nowther ſowl nor breau</l>
                     <l>And Iſe ſeay howl, I knaw nut what to deau:</l>
                     <l>The Fatt's all ſtorken'd here, a ſham to ſee,</l>
                     <l>I wad this griſely Cat war hang'd for me,</l>
                     <l>Hame's hamely, if it be neer ſeay poor they ſay,</l>
                     <l>And wee're but like to have poor Faire to day:</l>
                     <l>Here's mad warke <hi>Hobb,</hi> ſpeer'th deaur &amp; flay back 'th Cat</l>
                     <l>There'ſt Backon in her Mouth, hit her a bat:</l>
                     <l>Weel deaun <hi>Hobb,</hi> heſta gitten't leauke it's there,</l>
                     <l>It's lytle warſe, it's traild' ith mucky Fleaur,</l>
                     <l>Here'ſt Gully liggin, call thy Mother ſeaun,</l>
                     <l>Iſe ſcrape it cleen, Iſe ſeaure it's now paſt Neaun,</l>
                     <l>Fye, Fye, If wee'd nut come juſt when we did,</l>
                     <l>Wee'd been miſliken'd of our Dinners <hi>Pegg:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>How ſeay I whemmeld Dubler owr'th Meat,</l>
                     <l>To keep it ſeaf and warm for you to Eat,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:58681:28"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>But'th Cat had eaten't all if wee'd nut been,</l>
                     <l>Dubler's broken, thou may truſt thy nawn Een;</l>
                     <l>This Backon macks me Sweat it's varra ſawt,</l>
                     <l>And its all reaſty teau, thats a warſe fawt:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>They that eat til they ſweat, and work till they't Cawd,</l>
                     <l>Sike Fowkes are fitter to hang than hawd:</l>
                     <l>Yan knaws nut how to pleaſe you you'r ſeay fickle</l>
                     <l>Sike Feauls as you, are in Dockin out Nettle:</l>
                     <l>All things are reet abroad, but nought at Hame,</l>
                     <l>You'l finnd a faut I ſeaur whore there is nane:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>I wad fain ſee a Fine Sun ſhiny day,</l>
                     <l>Here's wancle Weather for gitting of our Hay,</l>
                     <l>What ails our <hi>Tibb,</hi> that ſhe urles ſeay ith Neauke</l>
                     <l>Shees nut reet ſhe leauks an awd farrand Leauke:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <l>Fatther Ive gitten Cawd, I can ſcarſe Tawk</l>
                     <l>And my Snurles are ſeay ſayer ſtopt, I can nut Snawke</l>
                     <l>Nor ſnite my Noſe, my Teeth Datther in my head</l>
                     <l>Iſe grown ſeay Healdy, I mun gang to Bed:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:58681:28"/>
I may thank my ſell for ſitting barehead,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut wilfull Fowkes, Duz never want weay its ſaid.</l>
                     <l>How duz my Coſen <hi>Tibb</hi> Naunt I mun nut ſtay,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> hard ſhe gat a Cawd the other day,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Ey wellaneerin will ta gang and ſee,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he's aboonith Chawmber, thou may clim upth Stee</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hees on a Dovening now gang Deftly <hi>Nan,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And mack as little din as ee'r thou can:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Your mains flaid, ther's an awd ſaying you knaw</l>
                     <l>That there's neay Carrion can kill a Craw:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhe be nut as dead as a deaur Naile,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e mack her flyer, and ſemper like fleſh Cael;</l>
                     <l>Thou Covers <hi>Tibb,</hi> I ſee thou's nut yet dead,</l>
                     <l>Leauk at me Woman, and hawd up thy Head;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Ah <hi>Nan</hi> ſteek'th winderboard, &amp; mack it dark,</l>
                     <l>My Neen are varra fair, they ſtoun and wark,</l>
                     <l>Tey are ſeay Gunny and Furr'd up ſome time,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> can nut leauke at Leet nor ſee a Stime,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:58681:29"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, come, I can mack thee Leetſome &amp; Blithe,</l>
                     <l>Here will be thy awd Sweet-heart here Belive.</l>
                     <l>He teld me ſeay I ſaw him but laſt Neet,</l>
                     <l>O <hi>Tibb</hi> he is as fine as onny Kneet:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay <hi>Nan</hi> thou duz but Jybe, there's neay ſike thing,</l>
                     <l>He wooes another Laſs, and gave her a Ring:</l>
                     <l>For Change of Paſtures macks fat Cawves it's ſaid,</l>
                     <l>But Change of Women macks lean Knaves Iſe flaid</l>
                     <l>I thought he lov'd me weel, he made ſike ſhew,</l>
                     <l>But all's nut Gowd that gliſters, I ſee now,</l>
                     <l>O're micle of yea thing, I've oft heard ſay,</l>
                     <l>Is good for neathing: and ſeay I finnd this day,</l>
                     <l>He was or'e keen to hawd as he began,</l>
                     <l>He was ſeay fond in Love as neer was Man,</l>
                     <l>But I may lye me down now, Seigh and Sob,</l>
                     <l>He cares neay mare for me now than a Dog:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>Away, away great Feaul tack thou neay Care</l>
                     <l>He ſwears that hee'l love thee for evermare;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:58681:29"/>
And ſayes as ever he whopes his Saul to ſave,</l>
                     <l>Hee'l either wed to thee, or tull his Grave;</l>
                     <l>Wayes me he never meawted thou was ill,</l>
                     <l>But all is weel that ends weel I can tell:</l>
                     <l>He had come titter <hi>Tibb,</hi> if he had knawn,</l>
                     <l>Thou war ſeay Ill, what woman hee's thy nawn;</l>
                     <l>He ſayes hee'd leather tack thee in thy Smock,</l>
                     <l>Then ſome with Fifty Pund, means is but Muck:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou macks me laugh <hi>Nan,</hi> if all be true thou ſaies</l>
                     <l>I whope that than Iſe ſee ſome Joyful dayes,</l>
                     <l>Hee's made me heve monny a ſad Heart,</l>
                     <l>I thowght he'd left me and wad nut tack my part:</l>
                     <l>But then ſometimes I thought it's a black Crake,</l>
                     <l>That never to her ſell can get a Make:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>The reaſon why he duz nut cume and gang,</l>
                     <l>He ſayes Love me leetly, and Love me lang</l>
                     <l>There's luck in leizure, he'd heve your loves tack hawd</l>
                     <l>He ſayes he's heard that haet love is ſeaun cawd:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:58681:30"/>
He can love the Houſe weel that hes <hi>Tibb</hi> in,</l>
                     <l>And nut be alwayes Rideing o'th Riggin</l>
                     <l>Next time he comes he'l tell thee all his Mind:</l>
                     <l>Seay be nut Stanfra but loving and kind:</l>
                     <l>And let him kiſs and grape teau if he will,</l>
                     <l>Thou's neer warſe woman, for there's nean can tell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <l>He's had neay want of that, w<hi>
                           <hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
                        </hi> macks me think</l>
                     <l>The Proverbs true that proffer'd things duz ſtink:</l>
                     <l>The things that we heve deaun Iſe arfe to tell,</l>
                     <l>But I ſuppoſe thou's deaun the ſame with <hi>Will:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray thee tell me <hi>Tibb,</hi> tell me woman ſeaun</l>
                     <l>And Ile tell thee what <hi>Will</hi> and I heve deaun,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <l>If I ſud tell the Reeks that we heve had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou'l kittle ſeay, it'l mack thee juſt ſtark mad:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou ſets me now Agog untill I hear,</l>
                     <l>Thou need nut bluſh come whiſper me 'ith Ear:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <l>What need I whiſper, thou knaws young wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men will,</l>
                     <l>To git a Lively Lad, uſe all their skill,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:58681:30"/>
He kiſt me firſt, did grape my Breeſts and than,</l>
                     <l>Went lawer down, thou knaws what teau dear <hi>Nan</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>Tell me I pray thee what did he <hi>Tibby,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Did he beat a Larum on thy Stiddy:</l>
                     <l>I knaw that thou wad let him deau it gratis,</l>
                     <l>If yance he gat but to thy <hi>Nunquam ſatis:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then thou wad cleave like <hi>Ivy</hi> to a Tree,</l>
                     <l>Come thou may tell here's neayn but thee &amp; me,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D,</speaker>
                     <l>I dare nut tell for flaid now of my Motther,</l>
                     <l>Pray thee be quiet <hi>Nan</hi> thou's ſike another,</l>
                     <l>I will nut tell unleſs thou will declare</l>
                     <l>What <hi>Will</hi> and thou did when you went to'th Faire</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>When <hi>Will</hi> did git to mine within an Inch,</l>
                     <l>O <hi>Tibb,</hi> how I did kittle than and winch:</l>
                     <l>I bluſh to tell what follow'd after that,</l>
                     <l>Young Men will heve a bit <hi>Tibb</hi> for their Cat:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <l>Wheeſht, wheeſht, my Mother's coming up I hear</l>
                     <l>And ſhees heard all our Tawke <hi>Nanny</hi> I fear:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:58681:31"/>
I dare nut ſpeak a word now leſs or mare,</l>
                     <l>For if ſhe hear ſhe'l whang me varra ſayer,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>Wad ſhe war hang'd, that cud nut ſtay belawe,</l>
                     <l>I had as leeve be fel'd, as nut all knaw:</l>
                     <l>Iſe hear all out, when I have time ro ſtay,</l>
                     <l>My Naunts juſt here now, farewel Ile away</l>
                     <l>I mun be ganging now, Iſe ſeaure its time,</l>
                     <l>I've nowther been at Kye, nor ſarra'd 'th Swine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>What iſta ganging <hi>Nan</hi> will thou nut ſtay,</l>
                     <l>How comes thy Clathes ſeay flurr'd Barne this Lownd day.</l>
                     <l>Thou's never Tite there's always ſomething wrang,</l>
                     <l>Wad ta ſaw thy ſell thou great Gammerſtang:</l>
                     <l>For ſham Woman Reet um down as ta geayes</l>
                     <l>Iſe ſeaur thou hes neay mence neer in thy Clayes</l>
                     <l>Beſeaur hereafter, Thou tack better Care,</l>
                     <l>For Meat is Mickle but Mence is mare:</l>
                     <l>Yonders our Owſe is loppen o're the Yate,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nan</hi> Slate him back, as thou gangs up'th Town gate;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58681:31"/>
                        <hi>N.</hi> Naunt Ile nut mell, Outleſs he war our awn,</l>
                     <l>What iſt weaud Owſe, that hiped at our Brawn,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Nea nea great Stags what a durdam thou macks,</l>
                     <l>It's him that brack down'th railes, to'th haver ſtacks</l>
                     <l>When thou gangs up the Town, thou'l knaw him ſeaun</l>
                     <l>He's a fine Flan Head, and a pure brown Greaun,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>Here's your <hi>Hob</hi> comming let him gang his ſell</l>
                     <l>I tell you plain, Ile nowther mack nor mell:</l>
                     <l>I heve neay time now up the Town to Rame</l>
                     <l>There is odd Charrs for me to deau at hame:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Husband is <hi>Hob</hi> gane to fetch back'th weaud Owſe</l>
                     <l>A wee bit ſine out o'th Fawd garth brack lowſe</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>If he can but dree, I ſaw him yeaud up'th Town,</l>
                     <l>And ſeay I think he's gane to ſlate him down;</l>
                     <l>Our Hay was ſeay ill gitten this wet year,</l>
                     <l>It hes nea Feauſan in't at all, I ſwear,</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Maugh</hi> did ſay, this Hay'l be nought you'l ſee,</l>
                     <l>I finnd an awd Ape now, hes an awd Ee:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:58681:32"/>
Wife what's become of my Spatterdaſhers,</l>
                     <l>Pray thee yeaud up'th Greeſe &amp; fetch'th Gamaſhaes</l>
                     <l>For I mun gang to'th Field, and fetch ſome Hay</l>
                     <l>And give Ilkin o'th Drapes ſome while I ſtay,</l>
                     <l>There is a Rencky Cow that beats all'th reſt,</l>
                     <l>And till I Fothet'd them I never wiſt,</l>
                     <l>Tother hes Booke and Bane, and are as tall</l>
                     <l>And yet ſhe macks um run on Snockſnarles all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Bring me our Hay Spade <hi>Hob,</hi> huſhta good Lad</l>
                     <l>Tack teaum, and gome thy feet what iſta mad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Some Roguehes Stown our Cawfhouſe deaur away</l>
                     <l>Mind <hi>Hobb</hi> if thou can Speer it out to day,</l>
                     <l>Outapont how that Hen gobbles up all'th Groate</l>
                     <l>Thur Birds are all Cumber Iſe cut their Throat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>You've ſetten'th Hen a Flowter, &amp; ſhe did fettle</l>
                     <l>To git her Birds all under the Lang Settle:</l>
                     <l>She gat a Gliffe o'th Dog, hit him a Nawpe,</l>
                     <l>Or els Iſe tack up'th Tengs and break his Scau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:58681:32"/>
                        <hi>F.</hi> What a durdams here, thou macks great warke</l>
                     <l>Theyl heve their gutts ſtampt out when it grows darke</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Stand by Caingell, let me crum um ſome Bread</l>
                     <l>Iſe arfe to put them out, becauſe o'th Glead,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>What a whanck's there, if thou ſike waſt do mack</l>
                     <l>I mun late'th Needle whore it never ſtack;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>They'l yeild ſome money, though it be little,</l>
                     <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>monny<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a little duz mack a Mickle:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>I care nut an they war all drown'd i'th Dike,</l>
                     <l>They're nut worth an Atchiſon, nor twenty ſike,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Your a cheap man trouble nut your Jobber Nowl</l>
                     <l>Ile give um ſome Trouts, reach me hither'th Bowl<hi>:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou's nought but babbles thou duz things tot'h hawves,</l>
                     <l>Thou'd mare need gang and mack ſome Cael for'th Cawves</l>
                     <l>They're ſtarv'd for want of meat hark how they Bleare,</l>
                     <l>When ſteed's ſtown thou mayſteek'th Stable deaur</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>You're full of Care, and neer had onny yet,</l>
                     <l>A pund of care'l nut pay an ounce of debt:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:58681:33"/>
Braggsa good Dog. I've heard my Granny tell,</l>
                     <l>But he was hang'd for Biting that was Ill<hi>:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If I'd nut tane mare care then you, Iſe ſeaur,</l>
                     <l>Before this day wee'd all been turn'd to'th deaur,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile yeild thy humour thou mun heve I ſee,</l>
                     <l>Or els I ſeaur, Thou'l neither Height nor Ree:</l>
                     <l>It's a good Horſe that duz never ſtumble,</l>
                     <l>And a good Wife that duz never grumble:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Come come for all this Clutter you do keepe,</l>
                     <l>You'd better have a Shrew, than heve a Sheep;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Come bring my Jerkin <hi>Tibb:</hi> Ile to'th Arvil,</l>
                     <l>You mans dead ſeay ſeaun, it macks me marvil:</l>
                     <l>I thought he leauk'd weel Yeſterday at Neaun,</l>
                     <l>I little dream'd he wad be dead ſeay ſeaun:</l>
                     <l>Come Wife mack ready will nut thou gang teau,</l>
                     <l>Let <hi>Tibb</hi> deau'th warke, if there be ought to deau:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay nay you know I cannut gang full weel,</l>
                     <l>For'th Cooper is to bring Hame'th Kirn and Skeel.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:58681:33"/>
Wya fare ye weel than, for Ile away,</l>
                     <l>They're boon to'th Kirke, and ſeay I mun nut ſtay.</l>
                     <l>I've gitten ſike a Whelke, as I com Hame</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uſt now it made my Gutts all kelke agane;</l>
                     <l>Mack haſt good <hi>Peg</hi> ſweepth houſe &amp; don thee ſeaun</l>
                     <l>Our Land-Lord Woman will be here by Neaun,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> had an Incklin out at'th Arvil Feaſt,</l>
                     <l>Methinks he macks deevliſh ſtickle but haſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Its time for me about the houſe to Trip,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le's be as welcome as watter into a Ship:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Sweep'th Arrans down, till all be clean neer lin,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s he'l leauk all Agye when he comes in<hi>:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> wad nut heve him here for onny thing,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lthough a Cat may leauke <hi>Pegg</hi> at a King<hi>:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hou leauks a Dozand leauke, rub or'e thy Face</l>
                     <l>With diſhclout, and put on thy Coife with Lace:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile into'th Loft, and don my Clathes, now <hi>Will</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ind you to git ſome Eldin ſeaun your ſell,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:58681:34"/>
And mack <hi>Tibb</hi> mend up'th Fire, its ommoſt ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>And let her rub down'th Table with a Clout:</l>
                     <l>Iſe ready now let him come when he will,</l>
                     <l>But nowther'th Why nor Filly we will ſell,</l>
                     <l>Let's nut caſt down our Hearts though he be ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>As lang lives a merry Heart as a ſad:</l>
                     <l>Its nut aboon Three weeks gane ſine'th Rent da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Husband what heve you gitten up to pay:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Ive Five Nobles <hi>Pegg,</hi> and ſome odd mone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou ſeld ſome Cheeſes hes thou onny:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Seven groats and a penny is all my Stock,</l>
                     <l>Thou knaws whore't ligs, Ive nowther Key nor lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray thee tell truly, hes thou neay mare,</l>
                     <l>Did Thou nut ſell ſome Garn at our laſt Fair;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>What if I did, heve I nut mare to pay,</l>
                     <l>Than I can mack of Trouts, Kirn-Milk &amp; W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wadta have me keaun, or deau that is warſe,</l>
                     <l>Turne Whore and Addle money with my Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:58681:34"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e have mare under my hands to gang about,</l>
                     <l>Thou's nut think that Ile be thy Underlout<hi>:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Thou ſnoutbands me ſayr, may I nut Jeſt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſeaur I meant neay harm to thee 'ith leaſt;</l>
                     <l>Come hither <hi>Hobb,</hi> what little Stock hes thou,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> knaw thou's Addled ſome with driveing Plew</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>The ſmall Stock, I've gitten up together,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Twelve Bodles, a Groat and Six pence Fatther,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>I mun borrow't <hi>Hobb,</hi> what iſta willing,</l>
                     <l>When I gitt mony thou's have a Shilling:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Iſe gang and fetch't, it's hard feſt in a Clout,</l>
                     <l>You may ſeaun lowſe't your ſell, and tack it out:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Here's three and three pence in odd money <hi>Peg,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That macks Forty Shillings, reet as my Leg.</l>
                     <l>Paſhions a Life, here'ſt Land-Lord juſt at deaur,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tand you by, Iſe ſpeak to him do nut fear:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L.</speaker>
                     <l>Iſe cum to ſee you, how duſta <hi>Billy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What macks Thee huſtle, thou's mare fawſe then ſilly</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:58681:35"/>
Thou Glincks &amp; glimes ſeay, I'd miſken'd thy Face</l>
                     <l>If thou had wont at onny other place:</l>
                     <l>Iſt God Morn, or God Deen, what ſeſta <hi>Will,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I think you heve nut din'd, heres a good ſmell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Leet pray you Land-lord, &amp; you ſeaun will knaw</l>
                     <l>I think my wife hes Pyes it'h Ewn to draw:</l>
                     <l>Thou caſts a Leet a Lantom <hi>Pegg,</hi> thou's mains fine,</l>
                     <l>Have you ſome Gueſts to come to day to Dine,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Wellaneering, wee'd need have every Neaun,</l>
                     <l>Something thats good to keep our Hearts aboon:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L.</speaker>
                     <l>But courſer Faire, I think might you content</l>
                     <l>You tack neay thought how to pay me my Rent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Good Land-Lord ſpare us we're but pour &amp; bare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whore'th Hedge is law, it's eath gitting 'ore there:</l>
                     <l>When yans down down with um, it duz appear</l>
                     <l>We heve had monny Loſles this ſame year:</l>
                     <l>Our Sheep are dead ith Rot, and you do knaw</l>
                     <l>The price of Butter now is varra law,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:58681:35"/>
Weeſe pay you as we mack't and as't coms in,</l>
                     <l>And you can have neay mare ot'h Cat but'th skin:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Here's Forty ſhillings, we heve neay mare,</l>
                     <l>Weeſe have a Cow to ſell at our neeſt Fair:</l>
                     <l>L. What can I deau with this it will nut clear,</l>
                     <l>And pay ſeay mickle, as ſtreights your awd Arrear,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Here's bad times, prey ya Land-Lord be content,</l>
                     <l>Forbear us but and you's heve all your Rent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>But it will be a lang time firſt Iſe feard,</l>
                     <l>And whiles'th Girſe grows Horſe ſtarves as Ive heard</l>
                     <l>Next time I come, you mun clear off I leauk,</l>
                     <l>Thur driblets mack me ſcrat, whor't duz nut yeauk</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>But you mun let us rive up ſome freſh grund,</l>
                     <l>Or els wee'l turn your Farme into your hand:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Wad ye'd gane titter, I had been neay warſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or your nut worth the warſt Fart of my A—</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou may gang when you will Iſe never care,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> git another Tennant I neer fear:</l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:58681:36"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:58681:36"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:58681:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58681:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:58681:38"/>
Wee'r Sattle'd here, and ſeay to ſtir weer laith</l>
                     <l>But weel I wait, weeſe gether here nea Grath,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L.</speaker>
                     <l>You ill my Farme for you have ſaid to ſome,</l>
                     <l>Your quite undeaun and beggar'd ſine you c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Some Pikethanks for ill will hes teld you that,</l>
                     <l>An unquoth Dog hes monny barkers at,</l>
                     <l>Iſe Sackleſs on't Sir, by this fire that Reeks,</l>
                     <l>Ile ſwear't upon all Beauks that opens and ſteeks;</l>
                     <l>If we ſud ſwelt our hearts it will nut deau,</l>
                     <l>T'afford Sour Milk, and Bread and Rent up teau;</l>
                     <l>Yet of your Farm, I neer ſaid an ill word,</l>
                     <l>To onny Body I will beſworn Land-Lord:</l>
                     <l>I was teld, Iſt git Gowd Grapes here by ſome Fowke,</l>
                     <l>But now I ſee I've bought a Pig in a Poke,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L.</speaker>
                     <l>Away away if I ſud let you ſit,</l>
                     <l>Rent free I ſee you cud nut live on it,</l>
                     <l>Your Corn's as Rank as ever it can ſtand,</l>
                     <l>There's ſike a wreck, it ligs all down o'th Land,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:58681:38"/>
And yet you ſay your Farm is ſtarke 'oth Rent,</l>
                     <l>And you for Tenants give me neay content,</l>
                     <l>You cannut pay nor I cannut forbear,</l>
                     <l>Provide ſeay for you ſelves another year;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee'r nut ſea Browden on't as you ſuppoſe,</l>
                     <l>I think langer we ſtay the mare weeſe loſe:</l>
                     <l>Wadwe'd nee'r kend your Farm, nor had cum here</l>
                     <l>But bought wit's beſt if it coſt nut 'ore dear,</l>
                     <l>There's neay Feaul like to'th awd Feaul, I may ſay</l>
                     <l>They that are bund I ſee they mun obey,</l>
                     <l>The time that we com here, we've cauſe to Curſe,</l>
                     <l>A tumbling Stane I ſee neer gathers Moſs:</l>
                     <l>We war o're weel before and did nut wait,</l>
                     <l>And now we may the time rue, when'ts ore late.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L.</speaker>
                     <l>Com, com, for all your goodly Cracks &amp; Brags,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll Husbands and Sluggards, mun gang in Rags:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f you aw'd Money when you com to'th Farme,</l>
                     <l>Your Creditors not it heve deaun you harm:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:58681:39"/>
If all your Stock be gane lean to your Kin,</l>
                     <l>Near is my Sarke, but nearer is my Skin;</l>
                     <l>Charity begins at Hame Iſe nut bund</l>
                     <l>To let you live Rent free upon my grund:</l>
                     <l>There's neay ſell like to'th awne ſell; yeu've Farmes ane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Offer'd you ſay, God ſpeed you, Iſe nee'r Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>A weaud Horſe I've heard it oft Reported</l>
                     <l>And a Rotten Harrow are ſeaun parted:</l>
                     <l>Fare weel, Iſe weay to finnd'th awd ſaying tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>It's an ill made Bargain, whore beath Parties Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>I've ſet our Land-Lord forward, wife hee's gan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Hob</hi>'s nut weel, he's a baſe ſtincking yane</l>
                     <l>He's troubl'd with worms, he can nut Sleep nor Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Give him Wormſeed and Treacle pray thee <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Weay worth this traſh, Iſe flaid my Lad's undeau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>He's varra Seek, it works at his Heart Speaun:</l>
                     <l>To Morne I'le gang to'th Market, and hire <hi>Tibb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Peggy</hi> Thou thy Sell, ſall Spin out'th Web<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:58681:39"/>
Why a Husband, you may deau what you will,</l>
                     <l>If I be weel. Iſe git it deaun my ſell;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>How deaye all, what Naunt as I hear ſay,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tibby</hi> hes tane a Godspenny to day:</l>
                     <l>Iſe come to knaw before I gang to Bed,</l>
                     <l>I thought this <hi>Martinmas</hi> ſhe wad be wed</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Wayes is me ſhe's ore Young for a good Man,</l>
                     <l>There's mare Fowks wed than keeps good Houſes <hi>Nan</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>She's Booke and Bane aneugh I knaw that's true</l>
                     <l>But ill weed waxes faſt and ſeay duz Thou:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>Ore young ſay you, I ſeaure ſhe's gane eighteen</l>
                     <l>And few but at that age, they are Man keen:</l>
                     <l>Pray you what Age war you when you did wed,</l>
                     <l>At ſixteen Naunt you loſt your Maidenhead:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>But they that wed before they'r wiſe, it's ſaid</l>
                     <l>Will dee before they thrive, and ſeay Iſe flaid</l>
                     <l>Will Thou and She, and all ſike Flirtigiggs,</l>
                     <l>That's fit for nought but ſerving Brewſter Piggs</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:58681:40"/>
I marvel thy Mother gits nut thee a Dame,</l>
                     <l>It's fitter for thee then to ſtay at Hame,</l>
                     <l>To ſlaver and Spin, and run an odd Char</l>
                     <l>A good Service war better for thee farr:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N,</speaker>
                     <l>What ſike an a Service as <hi>Tibbs</hi> to have,</l>
                     <l>I had as leeve be carrid to my Grave;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>How ſea what ails her Service can thou tell</l>
                     <l>Thou'l nowther let her thrive, nor thrive thy ſell:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>I hear <hi>Tibb</hi> is to gang to Miſtreſs <hi>Nice,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>She'l Rue, I'le warrant more than yance or twice,</l>
                     <l>She'l deal her Neaves about her, I hear tell,</l>
                     <l>She's timerous to pleaſe, and varra Fell,</l>
                     <l>Firſt thing that comes to hand ſhe'l let it flee,</l>
                     <l>Neans yable to abide her Crueltie;</l>
                     <l>She'l Nawpe and Nevel them without a Cauſe,</l>
                     <l>She'l make them late their teeth Naunt in their Hawſe</l>
                     <l>She's kittle of her hands, &amp; of her tongue ſeay rife,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Tibb</hi> Iſe ſeaure will have but an ill Life;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:58681:40"/>
Ile lay a Wager that <hi>Tibb</hi> never ſtayes</l>
                     <l>A New Meaun, and an awd, nay nut ten dayes:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou's had a good Layer Fatther <hi>Nan</hi> I gueſs,</l>
                     <l>Or els I ſeaur, thou never cud tell this;</l>
                     <l>Birlady but my Barne ſhall never be</l>
                     <l>A Battingſtock for her, Thou's plainly ſee:</l>
                     <l>Her Godſpenny, ſall be ſent back to Moarn,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tibbs</hi> ſtay at Hame with me <hi>Nan</hi> Ile beſworne;</l>
                     <l>I knaw here'l be a Sain'd for her to come,</l>
                     <l>But Iſe nee'r care, although her Miſtreſs Gloom,</l>
                     <l>My Laſs ſall nowther Dame nor Miſtreſs have,</l>
                     <l>Leather then gang to be a perfect Slave;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>My Neem's now coming farewel Ile to Bed,</l>
                     <l>I've ſitten till my Feet's as caw'd as Lead;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay prethee ſtay <hi>Nan</hi> but a wirly Bit,</l>
                     <l>I heve ſome Garne to ſend with thee to Lit,</l>
                     <l>I ſtale a Keſlup <hi>Nan,</hi> fra thy Fatther,</l>
                     <l>Which made me a deel of dainty preaſer:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:58681:41"/>
But Ill gitten, Ill gane, is true I finnd,</l>
                     <l>For it's all ſcatter'd, and's made an ill end:</l>
                     <l>Sea pray thee lend me a little Earning</l>
                     <l>For we mun mack ſome Cheeſe in the Morning:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>Let <hi>Tibb</hi> come 'ore as ſeaun as ſhe gits up,</l>
                     <l>And I ſall ſend you back by her a ſoape:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>What haſt's thou in ſtay and tack a drink <hi>Nan</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>There's Beer o'th Table, 'ith little Can,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>N.</speaker>
                     <l>This Drink's all dowl'd, how lang iſt ſine't was drawn</l>
                     <l>It is nut hawfe ſea freſh Naunt as our awn:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Yon Town's a dree way off <hi>Pegg,</hi> Iſe ſare tire'd</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tibb</hi> is all Jarbil'd, and Iſe baſely Mire'd:</l>
                     <l>As we went 'ore a Steel out ſtarts a Hare,</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Tibb,</hi> gave ſike a Glent, it flaid her ſare:</l>
                     <l>We went into an Houſe, I loſt my Staff,</l>
                     <l>I finnd its true, Still Sew eats all the Draffe,</l>
                     <l>All Fowk's deny'd, but yan beyond the Board,</l>
                     <l>And he had ſtown't, and never ſaid a word,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:58681:41"/>
How duſta Wife, thou is nut weel I think,</l>
                     <l>Thou graines varra ſare, wilta have a drink,</l>
                     <l>A grunting Horſe, and graining Wiſe, nee'r will</l>
                     <l>Their Rider fail, as I have heard Fowks tell,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Wya wya, I can bide your Scoffs and ſcornes</l>
                     <l>But God be thank'd a Curſt Cow gits ſhort Horns</l>
                     <l>You'd leather ſee me hanging weel I wait,</l>
                     <l>Than ſee me ganging up and down'th Town gate,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>You meauſe wife as ye uſe, Iſe neay ſike man,</l>
                     <l>I can nut pleaſe I ſee deau what I can,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>You are unſawncy, I think by my life,</l>
                     <l>With tawkin to you I heve broken my Knife:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>It's eath to mack'th Barne greet whore'th lip doth hing</l>
                     <l>You Gloom ſeay Wife, I thought you'd have a Fling</l>
                     <l>At me, or ſome els in the Houſe, ee'r Neet,</l>
                     <l>Something is alwayes wrang, all's never reet,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Gloom Co yea, it macks me as ſeeke as a Horſe,</l>
                     <l>Never to have a penny in my Purſe:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:58681:42"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Better's a comming pray thee do not wreak,</l>
                     <l>What Woman but for hope the Heart wad break:</l>
                     <l>God nee'r ſent Mouths, but he ſent Meat alway,</l>
                     <l>After fowl Weather followes a fair day:</l>
                     <l>That Man falls law that nee'r again duz Riſe,</l>
                     <l>Hope weell and have weell, is ſaid by the wiſe</l>
                     <l>I nee'r fear, but Fortune again will ſmile,</l>
                     <l>If we can have but patience for a while:</l>
                     <l>We ſall heve Luck Golore tack thou neay Care,</l>
                     <l>Though we at preſent be but varra Bare:</l>
                     <l>Some Riſe and ſome do fall ſtrangely we ſee,</l>
                     <l>Give a man Luck and thraw him into'th Sea.</l>
                     <l>Here's good Tobacco Wife it coſt a prindle,</l>
                     <l>How mun I leet my Pipe, Whaugh here's nea Ingle:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>What need you Rame ſeay, you ſee'th fire's gane</l>
                     <l>Poul out your Touchwood, box, Steel, &amp; flint ſtane,</l>
                     <l>Then ſtrike a Fire, and leet a Seave I Reed,</l>
                     <l>And ſmeauke your Pipe before we gang to Bed:</l>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:58681:42"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>F.</speaker>
                     <l>Unfeſt my Collar poynt Wife, Than let us Kiſs,</l>
                     <l>And pray for Love, mell them whore ther nean is.</l>
                     <l>What din is yon, lets gang to'th deaur good wife,</l>
                     <l>And Lithe, yonders ſome Flight, I lay my Life<hi>:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <l>Marry Husband you have a ſpecial gueſs,</l>
                     <l>Hark you what warke, yonders 'tween <hi>Nell</hi> &amp; <hi>Beſs</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A Cruel Flight begins, Amel tweay former Friends.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>N.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou Ugly Whore what wark made thou laſt Neet,</l>
                        <l>Thou deſerves douking ift hou had thy Reet;</l>
                        <l>That wad ceaul thy ſawt A—thou fulſome Bitch,</l>
                        <l>O Rotten Jade thou gave young <hi>Nobbs</hi> the Itch:</l>
                        <l>Laſt time he clapperclaw'd thy Reeking A—</l>
                        <l>He may be glad and fain it was neay warſe:</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>B.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou lucken-brow'd Trull, there's nean warſe than thy ſell</l>
                        <l>Thou went to ceaul thy Tail thou knaws at'th well</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="74" facs="tcp:58681:43"/>
When every griſely Scab it was ſeay big,</l>
                        <l>And ſare that thou cud neither ſit nor lig:</l>
                        <l>I neer Beſh—my ſell, as thou did Bitch,</l>
                        <l>When 'th Fellow wrought ſeay ſare he gat a ſtitch</l>
                        <l>Thou cud not git him off thy Belly Jade,</l>
                        <l>Till thou was forced to cry our for Aide,</l>
                        <l>And than'th whors bird thy Daughter <hi>Jan</hi> com in</l>
                        <l>And pould him of, and druſt &amp; made thee clean:</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>N.</speaker>
                        <l>I ſcorn thy words thou filthy Refie Jade,</l>
                        <l>Thou's gitten an 'ore heat Bitch with thy Trade,</l>
                        <l>Geay ſhack thy Scabs off Whore, &amp; weſh thy skin:</l>
                        <l>Thou ſtands mare need than I of macking clean:</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>B.</speaker>
                        <l>Hang thee whore, hang thee, I never was laid yet</l>
                        <l>Between two Feather Beds, to get a Sweat:</l>
                        <l>My hair did nee'r come off thon dirty Drab,</l>
                        <l>As thine did when thy Noſe was in a Scab;</l>
                        <l>I ne'r was laid down druncken on a Bed,</l>
                        <l>With all my Clathes poul'd up whore to my head,</l>
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:58681:43"/>
                        <l>And ſea left faſt aſleep with a great Candle</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>urning between thy Houghs, that all meet handle,</l>
                        <l>And then deau what they wad thou druncken Sew,</l>
                        <l>Thy Tallow face is like to mack me Spew:</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. How lang iſt fine the Lads did ſhout and hollow</l>
                        <l>And after thee with Rotten Eggs did follow:</l>
                        <l>Thou mawky whore, thou hes forgitten ſeaur,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ine'th Cramer gat the up again a deaur,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>th midſt of all'th Towngate, and'th Lads com by;</l>
                        <l>And ſaw you at it, than they ſet up a Cry:</l>
                        <l>And than beath thou &amp; he away did ſneake,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f thou can ſay ought for thy ſell, Whore ſpeake,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>N.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou lees, thou lees, thou griſely Braſlen Face,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> nee'r was Pybald yet, ith Saddle place:</l>
                        <l>Nor had a Surgeon to Syring me,</l>
                        <l>As thou had Whore, when thou cud hardly ſee</l>
                        <l>Thy Head and Face, they war ſeay ſwell &amp; ſare,</l>
                        <l>That thou had ſcarcely left thee onny Haire:</l>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:58681:44"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>B.</speaker>
                        <l>As weel hair'd as thy ſell, Thou naſty Quea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Hang thee, thou fulſome Trull, thou's never clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Baſe Tantrill I never uſe to tack Neet Ramble</l>
                        <l>And heve my Clathes ram'd up 'ith Butchers Shamble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Ther's filthy ſtinking Fleſh when thine liggs there,</l>
                        <l>O'th day time ſeaur there's nean can like ſike war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>N.</speaker>
                        <l>As good Ware as thy ſell Whore every whit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>I never was laid down on a Midden yet,</l>
                        <l>With a Drunken Tinkler fund at warke</l>
                        <l>Between my Legs Whore; it was nut ſeay dark,</l>
                        <l>But they cud plainly ſee that did gang by,</l>
                        <l>How ſweetly thou and thy Tinckler did lye,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>B,</speaker>
                        <l>Away, away Whore, thou tells up and down,</l>
                        <l>How monny Men hes laid with thee i'th Town,</l>
                        <l>Thou's a bold Whore, thy like was ſeldome ſeen,</l>
                        <l>I marvel neay good Wife Clawts out thy Neen;</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>N.</speaker>
                        <l>Clawt out my neen Whore, but Ile dill thy din,</l>
                        <l>I'le coul thy Haggas Bitch, if I begin,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="77" facs="tcp:58681:44"/>
Nay run nut Whore, Thou's nut ſeay leet of feaut,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e git thee an the Devil git the nut;</l>
                        <l>Nay Whore I've gitten haud, Ile coul thee down,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd ſhew thy Neighbours thy bald Scabby Crown</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Murder, Murder, good Neighbours help me ſeaun<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he Bites and Scrats, Iſe flaid Iſe be undeaun<hi>:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Weay worth this Whore, ſhe's riven all my pinner</l>
                        <l>My Coife, and Hankercher' as Iſe a Sinner:</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e mack thee pay for this Whore Ile beſworn,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e have a Warrant for the Jade to Moarn:</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. What prates ta ſtill, wad ta have mare yet Trull</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>efore I gang thou's have thy Belly full:</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>
                           <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <l>What runs ta Whore, heſta gitten'th deaur Sporne</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e have another Bout with thee to Morne:</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hou peeps yet whore, cum out again thou Bitch,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd I ſall Scrub off all thy Scabs, and Itch,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hink I've wheeſted thee Whore, for this Neet,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hou ſal be ſeaur of mare next time we meet:</l>
                     </sp>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:58681:45"/>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>B.</speaker>
                        <l>Wad, ta kiſs'd my A-thou Jarble tail'd Trull th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Thou's juſt like a Cow thats keen 'oth Bull no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Thou pins and decks thy, ſell to get a Ride</l>
                        <l>And nean that knaws thee will ſike Ket beſtrid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>N.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh Whore had I but thee here out again,</l>
                        <l>I'de mack thy Ribs to Reeke, and Guts to grai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>If ever I git thee in my Clutches,</l>
                        <l>Ile mack the fit Jade to gang on Crutches.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>The Authors Concluſion.</head>
                     <l>My Papers at an end Ile take my Eaſe,</l>
                     <l>Here's too much paines beſtow'd unleſs it plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="glossary">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:58681:45"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Alphabetical CLAVIS, Uunfolding the Meaning of all the</hi> York-ſhire <hi>Words made uſe of in the aforegoing</hi> DIALOG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E.</head>
                  <div n="A" type="letter">
                     <head>A.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>ISe Arfe; <hi>that is</hi> I am afraid.</item>
                        <item>Auters; <hi>ſignifies</hi> ſtrange work, <hi>or</hi> ſtrange things.</item>
                        <item>Amell; <hi>is</hi> Between.</item>
                        <item>Awne; <hi>Signifies</hi> own.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Rive all dawds; <hi>is to</hi> tear all in pieces.</item>
                        <item>Ackwards; <hi>is</hi> when a beaſt lies back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and cannot riſe.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="80" facs="tcp:58681:46"/>
What ailes this deaur; <hi>is</hi> what's the matter with this door.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An</hi> Aumry; <hi>is</hi> a Cupboard to put bread or meat in.</item>
                        <item>Awd; <hi>is</hi> Old.</item>
                        <item>Awdfarrand; <hi>is</hi> grave and ſober.</item>
                        <item>Aboon; <hi>is</hi> above,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> ſet one Agog; <hi>is</hi> to make one long or deſire,</item>
                        <item>Aſta; <hi>Signifies</hi> as thou,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An</hi> Atchiſon; <hi>is</hi> a Scot'ch Coyne worth fower Bodles,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An</hi> Arvill; <hi>is</hi> a Funeral.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> look Agye is to look aſide.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="B" type="letter">
                     <head>B.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Barne; <hi>is</hi> a Child,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Battin; <hi>is</hi> the Straw of two Sheaves foulded together.</item>
                        <item>Behawfe; <hi>is</hi> behalf.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="81" facs="tcp:58681:46"/>
                           <hi>To</hi> Batt'n; <hi>ſignifies</hi> to feed <hi>or</hi> like well.</item>
                        <item>Beeſtlings; <hi>is</hi> the firſt milk after Calv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
                        <item>Belive; <hi>is</hi> in the Evening,</item>
                        <item>Burne, <hi>is</hi> water.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> blend, <hi>is</hi> to mix <hi>or</hi> put together.</item>
                        <item>Baurghwans, <hi>are</hi> horſe Collars,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> bide billinge at, <hi>is</hi> to abide work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at.</item>
                        <item>Breckins, <hi>ſignifies</hi> Fearn.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Bauke, <hi>is</hi> a Balke.</item>
                        <item>Blendings, <hi>are</hi> Beans and Peaſe mixed together.</item>
                        <item>Bigg, <hi>is</hi> of the nature of Barly, <hi>and makes good Malt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Bull ſegg, <hi>is</hi> a gelded Bull,</item>
                        <item>Backon, <hi>is</hi> Bacon.</item>
                        <item>Beclarted, <hi>is</hi> Beſmeared or Bedaub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> bend Kitt, <hi>is</hi> a kind of a great Can with a Cover.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="82" facs="tcp:58681:47"/>
                           <hi>A</hi> Bleacher, <hi>is</hi> a whiteſter of Cloath.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Bakin, <hi>is</hi> Corn put up to ſend to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Mill for bread.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Beck, <hi>is</hi> a River.</item>
                        <item>Bannocks, <hi>are</hi> Cakes baked before th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> fire.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Back-ſtone, <hi>is</hi> a ſtone or iron to bak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Cakes on.</item>
                        <item>Blithe, <hi>is</hi> glad.</item>
                        <item>Breeſts, <hi>are</hi> breaſts.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Brawne, <hi>is</hi> a Boar.</item>
                        <item>Booke and bane, <hi>ſignifies</hi> luſty an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſtrong.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> bleare, <hi>is</hi> to roar and cry.</item>
                        <item>Twolve Bodles, <hi>ſignifies</hi> two pence,</item>
                        <item>To be browden on a thing, <hi>is</hi> to be fon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> on a thing.</item>
                        <item>Birlady, <hi>is</hi> by our Lady.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> batting ſtock, <hi>is</hi> a beating ſtock,</item>
                        <item>Beath, <hi>is</hi> both.</item>
                        <item>Breau, <hi>is</hi> ſupping Meat, or Gravy and fat for brewis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="C" type="letter">
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:58681:47"/>
                     <head>C.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>CRockie, <hi>is</hi> a little Scotch Cowe.</item>
                        <item>Cawven, <hi>is</hi> Calved.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Cowe cleening, <hi>is</hi> the bag that hangs at the Cows Box after ſhe hath new Calved.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Cawfe, <hi>is</hi> a Calfe.</item>
                        <item>Cawd, <hi>is</hi> cold.</item>
                        <item>Caell, <hi>are</hi> Potage.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Ceauke, is to Cook.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Clawt; is to tear or pull.</item>
                        <item>Caſſons, <hi>are</hi> dryed Cow turds,</item>
                        <item>Caffe, <hi>is</hi> Chaffe.</item>
                        <item>Like to clem, <hi>is</hi> very dry ready to choak.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Carle Cat, <hi>is</hi> a dog-Cat, or Hee Cat.</item>
                        <item>Nought Cottens weell, <hi>is</hi> Nothing goes right.</item>
                        <item>Cud, <hi>is</hi> could.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="84" facs="tcp:58681:48"/>
Chaumber, is a Chamber.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Crawe, <hi>or</hi> a Crake, is a Crow.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Cover, is to recover.</item>
                        <item>Clathes, <hi>are</hi> Clothes.</item>
                        <item>Cumber, is trouble.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Caingel, is a toothy crabbed fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> keep a clutter, is to make a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtir.</item>
                        <item>Coyea, is quoth you.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Ceaul, is to cool.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Clapperclawe, is to work earneſtly <hi>or</hi> beat or Fight earneſtly.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Crammer, is a Bowle ſewer.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Cool ones Haggas, is to beat on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſoundly.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="D" type="letter">
                     <head>D.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>ISe dinge, <hi>that is</hi> I ſhall beat.</item>
                        <item>Deft, is pritty.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="85" facs="tcp:58681:48"/>
Daft, is fond <hi>or</hi> fooliſh.</item>
                        <item>Deaun, is done.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Dubler, is a Diſh to lay Meat on.</item>
                        <item>Dench'd, is finely Mouthed <hi>or</hi> Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</item>
                        <item>Draffe, is Graines.</item>
                        <item>Deau, is do.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Deaur, is a door.</item>
                        <item>Degg-bound, is mightily ſwelled in the Belly.</item>
                        <item>Dittin, is Morter to ſtop up the Oven withal.</item>
                        <item>Dayugh, is Dough.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Deet, is to wipe and make clean.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Dodd Sheep, is to cut the wool away about their Tailes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Datther, is to Tremble with cold.</item>
                        <item>Duz, <hi>ſignifies</hi> does.</item>
                        <item>Deftly, is ſoftly <hi>or</hi> leaſurely.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Dovening, is a ſlumber.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="86" facs="tcp:58681:49"/>
Din, <hi>is</hi> noyſe.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Durdam, <hi>is</hi> a great noyſe or ſtir.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> dree, <hi>is</hi> to hold out, <hi>or</hi> be able to go.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> dree way of, <hi>is</hi> a long way off,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> drape, <hi>is</hi> a Cow to be fatted that gives no milk.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Dike, <hi>is</hi> a little Pond or watery place.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Don, <hi>is</hi> to put ones Clothes on,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> dozand leauke, <hi>is</hi> an old withered look.</item>
                        <item>Duſta, <hi>is</hi> does thou.</item>
                        <item>Driblets, <hi>are</hi> ſmall inconſiderable things.</item>
                        <item>Dowl'd, <hi>is</hi> dead <hi>or</hi> flatt, and not brisk.</item>
                        <item>Druſt, <hi>ſignifies</hi> dreſt.</item>
                        <item>To deck one ſelf, <hi>is</hi> to make them trim and fine.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="E" type="letter">
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:58681:49"/>
                     <head>E.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>EEn, <hi>are</hi> Eyes.</item>
                        <item>Ewes, is an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dder,</item>
                        <item>Ey, ey; is Yes, Yes.</item>
                        <item>Eard, is Earth.</item>
                        <item>Ewn, is an Oven,</item>
                        <item>Earnder, is the forenoon,</item>
                        <item>Eldin, is Wood and ſticks for the fire,</item>
                        <item>Eath, is eaſie.</item>
                        <item>Earning, is Rennet to make Cheeſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="F" type="letter">
                     <head>F.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>FLaid, is afraid.</item>
                        <item>Feaut, is a foot.</item>
                        <item>Fra, is from</item>
                        <item>Finnd, is find.</item>
                        <item>Fawt, is fault.</item>
                        <item>Faine, is glad.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="88" facs="tcp:58681:50"/>
Feawls, is Fooles.</item>
                        <item>Fund, is found.</item>
                        <item>Flung, is thrown.</item>
                        <item>Fleaure, is floor.</item>
                        <item>Faugh, is Fallow.</item>
                        <item>Fondly, is fooliſhly.</item>
                        <item>Fowkes, is Folk.</item>
                        <item>Feck, is the moſt <hi>or</hi> greateſt part.</item>
                        <item>Fogg, is freſh Graſs that comes after Mowing.</item>
                        <item>Feald, is hid.</item>
                        <item>Fruggin, is a Pole to ſtir in the Oven when it is heated to ſtir the aſhes up.</item>
                        <item>Flyer, is to laugh.</item>
                        <item>Feard, is afraid.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> be feld, is to be knocked down.</item>
                        <item>Flur'd, is all Ruffled.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Flan head, is a broad large head.</item>
                        <item>Feauſan, is Taſte <hi>or</hi> moiſture.</item>
                        <item>Flowter, is when one is angry <hi>or</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="89" facs="tcp:58681:50"/>
                           <hi>To</hi> Fettle, is to make ready, <hi>or</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Filly, is a Mare Foale, <hi>or</hi> young Mare,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Feſt, is to tye.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Flirtigiggs, is a wanton fond Laſs.</item>
                        <item>Fell, is fierce and keen.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Flight, is a Scoulding-match.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="G" type="letter">
                     <head>G.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>BY</hi> Grape, <hi>is by</hi> grope.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Greet, is to weep.</item>
                        <item>Geay, is go.</item>
                        <item>Town-gate, is the Town Street.</item>
                        <item>Gang, is go.</item>
                        <item>Groats, <hi>are</hi> Oatmeal.</item>
                        <item>Gawts <hi>and</hi> Gilts, <hi>are</hi> Hog-pigs, <hi>and</hi> Sow-pigs.</item>
                        <item>Gor, is miery <hi>or</hi> dirty.</item>
                        <item>Grip'd, is delv'd to drain away wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="90" facs="tcp:58681:51"/>
Geauſe, is a Gooſe.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Goame, is to mind.</item>
                        <item>Griſe, is Swine.</item>
                        <item>Girſe, is Graſs.</item>
                        <item>Glorr fatt, is very fat.</item>
                        <item>God Morn, is a good Morning to you.</item>
                        <item>Goddeen, is a good Evening.</item>
                        <item>Garne, is yarne.</item>
                        <item>To Gawve, is to ſtare.</item>
                        <item>Griſely, is ugly.</item>
                        <item>A Gully, is a houſe Knife, to cut bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Gunny and furr'd, is ſore running eyes.</item>
                        <item>Gammerſtang, is a great fooliſh wanton Girle.</item>
                        <item>Greaun, is a Month.</item>
                        <item>Greeſe, <hi>ſignifies</hi> Staires into a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</item>
                        <item>Gammaſhaes, <hi>are</hi> courſe Cloath Stoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings that butten upon other Stoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins to keep one warm.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="91" facs="tcp:58681:51"/>
                           <hi>To</hi> Gobble, is to eat greedily.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Gliſſe, is a ſudden ſight of a thing by chance.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Glead, is a Kite.</item>
                        <item>Granny, is a Grand-mother.</item>
                        <item>Glincks and Glimes, <hi>ſignifies</hi> to look cunningly.</item>
                        <item>Grath, is Riches.</item>
                        <item>Godspenny, is an Earneſt-penny,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Gloom, is to frown and be ſullen.</item>
                        <item>Grane, is to groan</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Glent, is to ſtart aſide.</item>
                        <item>Golore, is great plenty, <hi>or</hi> abundance,</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="H" type="letter">
                     <head>H.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>TO</hi> Hye, is to make haſt.</item>
                        <item>Harnes, <hi>ſignifies</hi> Braines,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Hipe, is to puſh with the Head,</item>
                        <item>Haud, is hold.</item>
                        <item>Hame, is Home,</item>
                        <item>Hobb, is Robert.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="92" facs="tcp:58681:52"/>
Haver, is Oates</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An</hi> Hurn, is a hoal behind the Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</item>
                        <item>Hinderends, are the Off all of Corn when it is winnowed.</item>
                        <item>Haet, is hot.</item>
                        <item>Hames, <hi>are</hi> the crooked pieces of wood that are put upon Horſe Collars.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An</hi> Hopper, is a Seed-lip, <hi>or</hi> Basket the Husband-men put their Seed-Corn in, when they ſowe their Land.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An</hi> Hemble, is an Hovel <hi>or</hi> houſe to put Cattel under, <hi>or</hi> Wayns <hi>or</hi> Carts into.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An</hi> Haver Riddle, is a Sive they uſe in Winnowing of Oates.</item>
                        <item>Harden, is Hempen.</item>
                        <item>Hing, <hi>ſignifies</hi> hang.</item>
                        <item>Helters, is Halters.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="93" facs="tcp:58681:52"/>
Holes <hi>and</hi> hurles, <hi>are</hi> odd dark blind holes in a houſe.</item>
                        <item>Hes, is hath.</item>
                        <item>Howle, is hungry.</item>
                        <item>Heſta, is has thou.</item>
                        <item>Heauldy, is one that is tender and cannot endure much cold.</item>
                        <item>Huſhta, <hi>ſignifies</hi> to hold faſt <hi>or</hi> mind ones feet.</item>
                        <item>Hawves, is halves.</item>
                        <item>Height <hi>nor</hi> Ree, <hi>ſignifies</hi> a wilful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that will not be perſwaded to any thing, but what they liſt.</item>
                        <item>Huſtle, is to ſhrug ones Shoulders.</item>
                        <item>Heart-ſpeaun, is the hole betwixt the Breaſt and Belly.</item>
                        <item>Hauſe, is the Throat.</item>
                        <item>Houghs, are the Leggs and Thighs.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="I" type="letter">
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:58681:53"/>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>ILfavart, is unhanſome.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Jet the Heck, is to put one to the door.</item>
                        <item>Jybe, is to mock <hi>or</hi> Jeer,</item>
                        <item>Iſta, <hi>ſignifies</hi> art thou,</item>
                        <item>Ilkin, is each one.</item>
                        <item>Jobber Nowle, <hi>ſignifies</hi> a Logger-head.</item>
                        <item>Jerkin, is a kind of a jacket <hi>or</hi> upper Dublet with four Skirts <hi>or</hi> laps.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An</hi> Inckline, <hi>ſignifies</hi> to have know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>or</hi> hear of a thing.</item>
                        <item>Iſe, <hi>ſignifies</hi> ſometimes I ſhall, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I am.</item>
                        <item>Iſt, <hi>ſignifies</hi> is it.</item>
                        <item>Jarbl'd, is dagled <hi>or</hi> dirty.</item>
                        <item>Ingle, <hi>ſignifies</hi> fire.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="K" type="letter">
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:58681:53"/>
                     <head>K.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>A Keauſtril, is a great bon'd courſe Creature.</item>
                        <item>A Keauke, is a Cook.</item>
                        <item>Knawe, is Know.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Kedge, is to fill one very full.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Kite, <hi>ſignifies</hi> the belly.</item>
                        <item>Kirne Milk, is butter Milk,</item>
                        <item>Knarl'd, is eaten and torn with the Teeth.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Kneet, is a Knight.</item>
                        <item>Keen, <hi>ſignifies</hi> Fierce <hi>or</hi> earneſt.</item>
                        <item>Knawn, is known,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Kittle, is to Tickle.</item>
                        <item>Kye, <hi>are</hi> Cowes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Kirne, is a Chirne.</item>
                        <item>A Kirk, is a Church.</item>
                        <item>Kelk <hi>ſignifies</hi> to Groan.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="L" type="letter">
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:58681:54"/>
                     <head>L.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>TO</hi> Late, is to ſeek.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Laer, is a Barn.</item>
                        <item>Lig, is to lye.</item>
                        <item>Leauke, is to look <hi>or</hi> behold.</item>
                        <item>Never Lin, <hi>ſignifies</hi> not to tire <hi>or</hi> give over.</item>
                        <item>Lang, is long.</item>
                        <item>To Lite, is to Rely on, <hi>or</hi> truſt to.</item>
                        <item>Liggin, is lying <hi>or</hi> reſting.</item>
                        <item>Lyth ye, Lyth ye, <hi>is as much as to ſay</hi> hark ye, hark ye.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Lug, is to tug, pull <hi>or</hi> bite.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Libber, is a Gelder.</item>
                        <item>Leeter, is Lighter.</item>
                        <item>For'th lang Lane, is when a thing is borrowed with an intention never to be pay'd again.</item>
                        <item>Leetſome, <hi>ſignifies</hi> to be pritty Chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="97" facs="tcp:58681:54"/>
Leather, is rather.</item>
                        <item>Lawer, is lower.</item>
                        <item>Lownd, is calm and mild.</item>
                        <item>Loppon, is Leaped.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Langſettle, is a long Wainſcot Bench to ſit on.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Loft, is a Chamber.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Leet, is to alight.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Lantom, is a pritty diſtance, <hi>or</hi> way off.</item>
                        <item>Laith, is loath.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Layer-father, is an Inſtructer, Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>or</hi> prompter.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Lit, is to dye.</item>
                        <item>Lucken Brow'd, is hanging knit Brows.</item>
                        <item>Thou lees, is thou lyes.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="M" type="letter">
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:58681:55"/>
                     <head>M.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>TO</hi> mack, is to make.</item>
                        <item>Mirk, is dark.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> mar, is to ſpoil.</item>
                        <item>Miſtetch, <hi>ſignifies</hi> to get an ill uſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Cuſtom.</item>
                        <item>Mell, is Between.</item>
                        <item>Mare, is more.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Meauſe, is wonder <hi>or</hi> admire.</item>
                        <item>Mun, is muſt.</item>
                        <item>Maut, is Malt.</item>
                        <item>Meay, is moe.</item>
                        <item>A Meer, is a Mare.</item>
                        <item>Maugh, is a brother-in-Law.</item>
                        <item>Meeterly, is indifferent.</item>
                        <item>Mawks, are Maddocks.</item>
                        <item>Miſlicken'd, is diſappointed.</item>
                        <item>Mains flaid, is much afraid.</item>
                        <item>Mickle is much.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="99" facs="tcp:58681:55"/>
Meauted, is thought, dreamed, <hi>or</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</item>
                        <item>A Make, is a fellow, <hi>or</hi> companion.</item>
                        <item>Mence, is handſomneſs, <hi>or</hi> Credit.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> marvil, is to admire <hi>or</hi> wonder.</item>
                        <item>Misken, is not to know.</item>
                        <item>Mains fain, is very glad.</item>
                        <item>Mains fine, is very fine.</item>
                        <item>Meaun, is the Moon.</item>
                        <item>Meauſe as you uſe, <hi>that is</hi> when one judgeth another according to their own doings.</item>
                        <item>Mawkie, is full of Maddocks.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Morne, is to morrow.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="N" type="letter">
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:58681:56"/>
                     <head>N.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>NAr, is near.</item>
                        <item>Neen, <hi>ſignifies</hi> Eyes.</item>
                        <item>Nut, is not.</item>
                        <item>Nean <hi>or</hi> Neayn, is none.</item>
                        <item>Neay, is no.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Newke <hi>or</hi> Neawke, is a Corner.</item>
                        <item>Neet, is night.</item>
                        <item>Neem, is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle.</item>
                        <item>Neer Rack, is never matter; <hi>or</hi> take no care.</item>
                        <item>Neawn, is Noon.</item>
                        <item>Nawn, is own.</item>
                        <item>Nowther, is neither.</item>
                        <item>Neeſt, is next.</item>
                        <item>Naupe <hi>and</hi> Nevill, is to beat <hi>and</hi> ſtrike.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="O" type="letter">
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:58681:56"/>
                     <head>O.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ght, is any thing.</item>
                        <item>Onny, is any.</item>
                        <item>Ownder, is the afternoon.</item>
                        <item>Owſe, is an Ox.</item>
                        <item>Odd Charrs, <hi>ſignifies</hi> triffling buſineſs, <hi>or</hi> ſmall Errands.</item>
                        <item>Ommoſt, is almoſt.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="P" type="letter">
                     <head>P.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>TO putt, is to puſh with the head.</item>
                        <item>Pratty; is handſome, <hi>or</hi> pritty.</item>
                        <item>Preauf, is proof.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> plew, is to plow.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> mack the Pot play, is to make the Pot boyl.</item>
                        <item>Pokes, <hi>are</hi> Sacks.</item>
                        <item>Pudding-pock, is the Pudding bag.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Pleugh, is a Plough.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="102" facs="tcp:58681:57"/>
It ploſhes, <hi>ſignifies</hi> to be all wet under foot.</item>
                        <item>Perry, is a little Cur Dog.</item>
                        <item>Puſom'd, is poyſon'd.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Pownd, is a Pond of water.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> preaze, is to preſſe towards a plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>or</hi> endeavour to go that way.</item>
                        <item>The Paete, is the head.</item>
                        <item>Preaſure, is Rennet to make Cheeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> withal.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Pringle, is a little ſilver Scotc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Coine about the bigneſſe of a penny with <hi>two xx.</hi> on it.</item>
                        <item>Pybald, is to be of two Colours.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> prate, is to talk ſaucily.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="R" type="letter">
                     <head>R.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>A Rape, is a Rope.</item>
                        <item>To Rout, is to roare.</item>
                        <item>Rive, is to tear.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="103" facs="tcp:58681:57"/>
Reek, is ſmoak.</item>
                        <item>A Reckincrewke, is the pot hanger.</item>
                        <item>I Reed, is I adviſe.</item>
                        <item>Reant, is root.</item>
                        <item>Remmon'd, is removed.</item>
                        <item>A Reel, is an inſtrument Women wind their linnen or hempen yarne on.</item>
                        <item>A Rock, is a Diſtaffe.</item>
                        <item>Ream Kit, is the Cream pot.</item>
                        <item>Reaſty, is when Bacon is yellow and taſte rank.</item>
                        <item>Reet, is right: <hi>To</hi> Reet a thing down, ir to make it ſmooth.</item>
                        <item>Riggin, is the Ridge of an houſe.</item>
                        <item>Reeks, is it ſmokes.</item>
                        <item>Rame, is to Rove, Rake, ſcrape, <hi>or</hi> pull.</item>
                        <item>Rencky, is great and large.</item>
                        <item>Ranck, is thick <hi>or</hi> throng.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> rue, is to repent.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="104" facs="tcp:58681:58"/>
Rife of Tongue, is quick and nimble of Tongue.</item>
                        <item>Reefie, is Scabby <hi>or</hi> Itchy,</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="S" type="letter">
                     <head>S.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>SIne, is ſince.</item>
                        <item>Sike, is ſuch.</item>
                        <item>Seaun, is quickly.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Skeell, is a Milk Pale, <hi>or</hi> Water Pale.</item>
                        <item>Sell, <hi>ſignifies</hi> ſelf.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Suckle, is to let a Calf ſuck the Dam or Mother.</item>
                        <item>Streay, is Straw.</item>
                        <item>Strangly, is ſtrongly.</item>
                        <item>Swamp, is empty or ſmal.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Sile, is a ſtrainer for Milk.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Spang ones gates, is to make haſt.</item>
                        <item>Snithe, is very cold <hi>and</hi> piercing.</item>
                        <item>Seaure, is ſure.</item>
                        <item>Smiddy, is a Black-Smiths Shop.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="105" facs="tcp:58681:58"/>
Specks, <hi>are</hi> long thin pieces of Iron which Husband-men nail upon their Ploughs, to ſave them from wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Sock, is the Plough ſhare to put on the Noſe of the Plough.</item>
                        <item>Sawt, is ſalt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Stag, is a young Colt.</item>
                        <item>Sarraes, <hi>ſignifies</hi> ſerves.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Shack-fork, <hi>is</hi> a ſtick with two grains which Thraſhers uſe to ſhake up the Straw with all, that all the Corn may fall out from amongſt it.</item>
                        <item>Steauls, are Stools to ſit on.</item>
                        <item>Swingle-trees, <hi>are</hi> crooked piecs of wood to which the Horſe Traces <hi>are</hi> made faſt behind the Horſes.</item>
                        <item>Strang, <hi>is</hi> ſtrong.</item>
                        <item>Seavy, <hi>is</hi> full of Ruſhes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="106" facs="tcp:58681:59"/>
A Seave, is a Ruſh that is drawn through in greaſe, which in ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poor houſes, they light up <hi>and</hi> burn inſtead of a Candle.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Saw Corn, is to ſow Corn.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Steg, is a Gander.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> ſteek <hi>or</hi> ſteck, is to ſhut.</item>
                        <item>A ſtand Heck, is a Cratch that ſtands on feet in a Fold-Yard, for Cattel to eat their Fodder out on.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Sneck, is a latch of a door <hi>or</hi> Gate,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> ſlate a Beaſt, is to hound a Dog at him.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> ſtick, is to Butcher and kill a thing.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> ſtramp, is to tread upon.</item>
                        <item>Skitter, is when Cattel Scoure, <hi>or</hi> ſhite thin.</item>
                        <item>Slocken, is to quench the thirſt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="107" facs="tcp:58681:59"/>
Side Lanyells, are hopples for Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</item>
                        <item>A Stane, is a ſtone.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Sneauskin, is a leather which Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have faſt at their Diſtaff, and lay upon their thigh to twirle their Spindle upon.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Spence, is a little place made with Wainſcot, <hi>or</hi> a Lattice to ſet Milk <hi>or</hi> drink in.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Slake heat, is to ſcale <hi>or</hi> looſe heat.</item>
                        <item>Sammaron, is a Cloath betvveen Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen and Hempen, not altogether ſo courſe as the one, <hi>nor</hi> fine as the other.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Seck, is a Sack.</item>
                        <item>Sheaun, <hi>are</hi> Shooes.</item>
                        <item>Slovvn, is ſtoln.</item>
                        <item>A Sark, is a ſhirt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="108" facs="tcp:58681:60"/>
Sowle, <hi>is</hi> all kind of moyſt <hi>or</hi> ſupping Victuals.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Storken, <hi>is</hi> to cool, <hi>or</hi> wax ſtiff <hi>or</hi> hard.</item>
                        <item>Seay, <hi>is</hi> ſo.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> ſpeer out a thing, <hi>is</hi> to enquire after a thing.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> ſpeer the Deaur, <hi>is</hi> to ſhut the door.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> whemmele a Bowlover a thing, <hi>is</hi> to cover it with a Bowle.</item>
                        <item>Snawke, <hi>is</hi> to ſmell.</item>
                        <item>Snurles, <hi>are</hi> the Noſtrils.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Snite, <hi>is</hi> to blow the Noſe.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Stee, <hi>is</hi> a Stye <hi>or</hi> Ladder.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> ſemper, <hi>is</hi> to ſmile.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> ſtown, <hi>is</hi> when a thing ſmarts.</item>
                        <item>Not to ſee a ſtime, <hi>is</hi> to be blind, <hi>and</hi> ſee nothing at all.</item>
                        <item>A Saul, <hi>is</hi> a ſoul.</item>
                        <item>Sad, <hi>is</hi> ſorrowful <hi>or</hi> Melancholly.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="109" facs="tcp:58681:60"/>
Stanfra, <hi>is</hi> backward, <hi>or</hi> unwilling.</item>
                        <item>Sud, <hi>is</hi> ſhould.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Stiddy, <hi>is</hi> an Anvill.</item>
                        <item>Spatterdaſhers, <hi>are</hi> things to put above ones Stockings to keep them clean from mire and dirt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> run on ſnack-ſnarles, is to run on heaps headlong together.</item>
                        <item>Where it never ſtack, is where it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtuck.</item>
                        <item>Sporn, is ſhut or cloſed.</item>
                        <item>Seſta, is ſayeſt thou.</item>
                        <item>Stickle but haſt, is very great haſt, <hi>or</hi> ſpeed.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> ſnoutband one, is to be very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry <hi>and</hi> haſty with one.</item>
                        <item>Stark at the Rent, is very dear at the Rent.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> ſcrat, is to ſcratch.</item>
                        <item>Sattl'd, is ſettled.</item>
                        <item>Sackleſs, is guiltleſs, <hi>or</hi> innocent.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="110" facs="tcp:58681:61"/>
                           <hi>To</hi> Swelt, is to dye.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Saind, <hi>is</hi> a Meſſenger <hi>or</hi> meſſage.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Soape, <hi>is</hi> a little quantity <hi>or</hi> ſup.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="T" type="letter">
                     <head>T.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Tee, <hi>is</hi> the ſtring the Cow Legs are made faſt withal whileſt ſhe is milked.</item>
                        <item>Tinye, <hi>is</hi> little.</item>
                        <item>Well tidded, <hi>is</hi> when a Cow hath a good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dder, <hi>and</hi> promiſeth fair for ſtore of milk.</item>
                        <item>Tweay, <hi>is</hi> two.</item>
                        <item>Thur, <hi>is</hi> theſe.</item>
                        <item>Tane, <hi>is</hi> taken.</item>
                        <item>Tawke, <hi>is</hi> talk.</item>
                        <item>Tewh, <hi>is</hi> tough.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="111" facs="tcp:58681:61"/>
Teaut, <hi>is</hi> to it.</item>
                        <item>Teaume, is time.</item>
                        <item>Teng'd, <hi>is</hi> ſtung <hi>or</hi> ſting'd.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Teaup, is a Ram.</item>
                        <item>Like to tawme, is like to ſwound.</item>
                        <item>Traild, is pull'd and dragged up and down.</item>
                        <item>Teau, is to.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Tantril, is an idle tatling Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</item>
                        <item>Titter, is quicker <hi>or</hi> ſooner.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Drull, is a mucky fowl Quean.</item>
                        <item>Tack, is to take.</item>
                        <item>Tengs, are Tonges.</item>
                        <item>Twonty, is twenty.</item>
                        <item>Trouts, <hi>are</hi> Curds.</item>
                        <item>Traſh, is green fruit, as Apples, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Timerous to pleaſe, is ill to pleaſe.</item>
                        <item>Touch-wood, is rotten Wood laid by
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58681:62"/>
to dry, that it may take fire at any ſpark given by a flint and ſteel.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="V" type="letter">
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>VArra, is very.</item>
                        <item>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcape, is to put one in mind of a thing that is not Convenient.</item>
                        <item>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncuths, <hi>ſignifies</hi> News.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> 
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rle, is to draw ones ſelf up on a heap.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An</hi> 
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderlout, is a kind of a ſlave, <hi>or</hi> Drudge.</item>
                        <item>An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>neuth Dog, is a ſtrange Dog.</item>
                        <item>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſawncy, is unluckie, <hi>or</hi> not fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> unfeſt, is to untye <hi>or</hi> unlooſe.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="W" type="letter">
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:58681:62"/>
                     <head>W.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>WArk, is work.</item>
                        <item>Weeſe, is we ſhall.</item>
                        <item>Whaugh, is a word of Admiration, as <hi>God bleſs us,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                        <item>Wally, Wally, is Good lack, good lack <hi>or</hi> Oh me, Oh me.</item>
                        <item>War, is were.</item>
                        <item>Wad, is would.</item>
                        <item>A Whye, is an Heifer.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> waite, is to know.</item>
                        <item>Whore, <hi>is</hi> Where.</item>
                        <item>Wya, <hi>is</hi> well.</item>
                        <item>Wheay, <hi>is</hi> Who.</item>
                        <item>Whickens, <hi>are</hi> roots of Weeds.</item>
                        <item>Whins, <hi>are</hi> Furz.</item>
                        <item>Wellaneerin. <hi>is</hi> Lackady, <hi>or</hi> Alas, alas.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Whaug one, <hi>is</hi> to beat one.</item>
                        <item>Wrang, <hi>is</hi> wrong.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="112" facs="tcp:58681:63"/>
                           <hi>A</hi> whanck, <hi>is</hi> a great piece.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Whelk, <hi>is</hi> a great fall.</item>
                        <item>Wont, is dwelt <hi>or</hi> lived.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> wreck, <hi>is</hi> aboundance.</item>
                        <item>Whewts of Girfe, <hi>are</hi> young freſh Piles <hi>or</hi> blades of Graſs.</item>
                        <item>Whig, <hi>is</hi> Clarified Whey, put up with Herbs to drink.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Whean Cat, is a ſhee Cat.</item>
                        <item>Warſe, <hi>is</hi> worſe.</item>
                        <item>Wayes is mee, <hi>is</hi> woes me.</item>
                        <item>Whilk, <hi>is</hi> which.</item>
                        <item>Weell, <hi>is</hi> well.</item>
                        <item>Wancle, <hi>is</hi> uncertain <hi>or</hi> changeable Weather.</item>
                        <item>Weay, <hi>is</hi> ſorrowful.</item>
                        <item>Wilta, <hi>is</hi> will thou.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> winch, <hi>is</hi> to Kick.</item>
                        <item>Wheſht, Wheſht, <hi>is</hi> peace, peace.</item>
                        <item>Wadta, <hi>is</hi> would thou.</item>
                        <item>Weand, <hi>is</hi> Mad.</item>
                        <item>
                           <pb n="113" facs="tcp:58681:63"/>
                           <hi>A</hi> Wee bitt, <hi>or</hi> Wirly bitt.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Wreak, <hi>is</hi> to fret and be angry.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Y" type="letter">
                     <head>Y.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>YAn, <hi>is</hi> one.</item>
                        <item>Yauds, are Horſes.</item>
                        <item>Yowes, <hi>are</hi> Yewes.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Yat, <hi>is</hi> a Gate.</item>
                        <item>Yance, <hi>is</hi> once.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Yeaud, <hi>is</hi> to go.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>To</hi> Yeauke, <hi>is</hi> to Itch.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The</hi> Yane, <hi>is</hi> the breath.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58681:64"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58681:64"/>
                  <head>A <hi>Catalague</hi> of ſome Books, Sold by <hi>Francis Hildyard,</hi> Bookſeller at the Signe of the Bible, in <hi>Stonegate;</hi> in <hi>York.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>GRotij Opera 4 <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Euſebij <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hiſtoria Eccles cum notis valeſij Gr. <hi>&amp;</hi> Lar. 3. <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sylvij Opera Medica <hi>fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Heiſechij Lexicon 4<hi>to.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Monaſticon Anglicanum 3 <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Matthaej Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Hiſtoria newly printed with a large Gloſe <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hortus Indicus Malabaricus, <hi>continens</hi> Regni Malabarici apud Indos celeberrimi omnis generis Plantas rariore, <hi>Latinis, Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baricis, Arabicis, &amp; Bramanum Character ibus nominibuſque expre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſs as,</hi> Unà cum Floribus, Fructibus &amp; Seminibus, naturali magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine à peritiſſimis pictoribus delineatas, &amp; ad vivui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t exhibitas, 2 <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Originis contra Ceſſum 4<hi>to.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>—contra Marcion. 4<hi>to.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. Hammond's Works now compleated in 4 <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. Jsaac Barrow's Works 2 <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. Willis Works Compleat, <hi>fol.</hi> Engliſh.</p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Brady's</hi> Introduction to the old Engliſh Hiſtory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ioſephus</hi> Works, newly reprinted, <hi>fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Pole</hi>'s Annotations on the Bible, <hi>fol.</hi> 1. <hi>vol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bakers</hi> Chronicle <hi>fol.</hi> newly reprinted.</p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Combers</hi> Companion to the Temple in one <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Works of the Author of <hi>The whole duty of Man, fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Grews</hi> Anatomy of Plants, upon Royal Paper, <hi>fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Salmons</hi> Iatrica ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Praxis Medendi, 4<hi>to.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>—Diſpenſatory 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>—Doron Medicum. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>—Synoptis Medicinae. 2 <hi>vol.</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>—Horae Mathmaticae 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sr. <hi>Ionas Moores</hi> Syſtem of the Mathmaticks, 4<hi>to.</hi> 2 <hi>vol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Itineareum totius ſacrae Scripturae, or the Travels of the holy Patriarchs, Prophets, Judges, Kings, our Saviour Chriſt and
<pb facs="tcp:58681:65"/>
his Apoſtles, as they are related in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hiſtory of the Bucaniers in <hi>America,</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>L'Eſtranges</hi> Obſervators, 1. <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>—Tracts, in two <hi>vol.</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Works of the famous Mathematician, Mr. <hi>Edmund Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A ſhort Dictionary Engliſh and French, with another French and Engliſh according to the preſent uſe, and Modern Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy, by <hi>Guy M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ege</hi> Gentleman</p>
                  <p>Contemplations Moral and Divine, by Sr. <hi>Matthew Hale</hi> Knight, late Chief Juſtice of the Kings Bench, 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Gibſons</hi> Anatomy of Humane Bodies Epitomized.</p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Patricks</hi> Paraphraſe on the Pſalms. 2 <hi>vol.</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>—Paraphraſe on <hi>Iob.</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>—Paraphraſe on <hi>Proverbs.</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>—Devout Chriſtian 12<hi>mo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>—Chriſtian Sacrifice, 12<hi>mo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Friendly Debate between a Conformiſt and a Non-conformiſt Short Diſcourſes upon the whole Commonprayer, deſigned to inform the Judgement, and excite the Devotion of ſuch as day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe the ſame, by <hi>Th. Comber, D. D.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plutarchs</hi> Lives done into Engliſh by ſeveral hands, the three firſt <hi>vol.</hi> being all that are yet extant.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plutarchs</hi> Morals, done in Engliſh by ſeveral hands, they two firſt <hi>vol.</hi> being all that are yet extant.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Creech's</hi> Tranſlation of <hi>Lucretius,</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>—Horace,</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>—Theocritus,</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="law" type="books">
                     <head>LAW BOOKS.</head>
                     <p>The Statutes at large by <hi>Ioſ. Keeble</hi> Eſq. <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>An Aſſiſtance to Juſtices of Peace by the ſame Authors. <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Plowdens' Commentaries, <hi>fol.</hi> newly reprinted.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Roles</hi> Grand Abridgement in two <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>—Reports, 2 <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cookes</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1. Reports in Engliſh, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>—12. and 13. Reports Eng. <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>—Inſtitutes in 4 <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Croke's</hi> Reports in Engliſh, <hi>fol.</hi> 3 <hi>vol.</hi> reprinted with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb facs="tcp:58681:65"/>
of many thouſand of References never before printed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Leonard's</hi> Reports Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t. in one <hi>vol. fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sheppard's</hi> Common Aſſurances. <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>—Grand Abridgment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2 <hi>vol.</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A New Book of Entries by Sr. <hi>Tho. Robinſon. fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Dalton's</hi> Juſtice of Peace <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>—Office of a Sheriff, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Brown's</hi> Entries <hi>fol.</hi> Compleat.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anderſon's</hi> Reports, <hi>fol.</hi> Compleat.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Moors</hi> Report, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hobarts</hi> Reports, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Modern</hi> Reports, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sidderfin's</hi> Reports, 1 and 2 parts, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Styles</hi> Reports, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Yelvertons</hi> Reports, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vaughan's</hi> Reports, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Huttons</hi> Reports, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Owen's</hi> Reports <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Littletons</hi> Reports, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Saviles</hi> Reports, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Dyers</hi> Reports, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pultons</hi> De pace Regis &amp; Regni <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cawleys</hi> Laws againſt Recuſant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Manlys</hi> Interpreter <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Officina</hi> Brevium, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sr. <hi>Orlando Bridgmans</hi> Preſidents, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vidians</hi> Entries, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Blounts</hi> Law Dictionary, <hi>fol.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Compleat Clerk, 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Weſts</hi> Preſidents 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Godolphins</hi> Abridgement of Eccleſiaſtical Laws, 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Brownlows</hi> and <hi>Goldsbroughs</hi> Reports 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Swinbourn</hi> of Wills, 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Swinbourn</hi> of Wills, 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Winggtes</hi> Abridgement of all the Statutes in force, and uſe untill this preſent year 1684. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Terms of the Law. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Clarks</hi> Guide all four parts. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Parſons Councellor, by Sir <hi>Simon Degg,</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Parſons Law.</p>
                     <p>The Laws of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Abridgement of <hi>Crokes</hi> Reports by <hi>W. Hughs.</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:58681:66"/>
                        <hi>Kitchin</hi> of Courts. 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hales</hi> Pleas of the Crown, 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And all ſorts of School Books, as alſo Pictures ingraved, Etch'd, and in Miſſintinto, Maps of ſeveral ſorts, both plain and Colloured.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58681:66"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
